<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Armatura Dei, or, A preparation for suffering in an evil day shewing how Christians are to bear sufferings, and what graces are requisite thereunto : suited for all good Christians in this present time / by Edward Polhil ..., Esq.</title>
            <author>Polhill, Edward, 1622-1694?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3431</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12375423</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12375423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60575</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55301)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60575)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 221:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Armatura Dei, or, A preparation for suffering in an evil day shewing how Christians are to bear sufferings, and what graces are requisite thereunto : suited for all good Christians in this present time / by Edward Polhil ..., Esq.</title>
                  <author>Polhill, Edward, 1622-1694?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Cockerill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Suffering --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60575:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60575:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ARMAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RA DEI:</hi> OR, A PREPARATION FOR SUFFERING IN <hi>An Evil Day:</hi> SHEWING How Chriſtians are to bear Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and what Graces are Requiſite thereunto: Suited for all good Chriſtians in this preſent Time.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD POLHIL</hi> of <hi>Burwaſh</hi> in
<hi>Suſſex,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Cockerill,</hi> at the
<hi>Three-Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60575:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60575:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT is the ſaying of Grave Divine, That in the School of Satan, the firſt <hi>A B C</hi> of Atheiſm is this, <hi>All theſe will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worſhip me;</hi> but in the School of Jeſus, the firſt <hi>A B C</hi> of Religion is this, <hi>If any man will be my Diſciple, let him deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and take up his Croſs, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me.</hi> Oppoſition is <hi>Evangelij Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> the Church hath the Croſs for its Inheritance: It is the Ordinance of God, That through Tribulation we muſt enter into his Kingdome: This hath been the way of the Saints in all Ages; The Cloud of Witneſſes have walked in it to Heaven; Jeſus Chriſt, the Captain
<pb facs="tcp:60575:3"/>of our Salvation, was made perfect through Sufferings; and therefore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who are to follow him whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth, muſt provide for the Croſs, Eſpecially at ſuch a time as this. Now, not only the common Lot of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, but the dark aſpect of the Times bid us prepare for Sufferings: Charity is cold, Differences are hot, Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration Vaniſhes, Enmity every where appears, Popery lifts up itſelf in the World, Proteſtants help on the Deſign, by deſtroying each other, Sin is gone up with a great cry to Heaven, black Clouds of wrath hang over our heads for it, the decayes of holy Love threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a removal of our Candleſtick, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs in Religion ſhews, that we are fit to be ſpued out of Gods mouth: Every one that hath Eyes in his Head, may ſee the tendency of ſuch things as theſe; and therefore Chriſtians have more than an ordinary Obligation on them to provide for the Croſs, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:60575:3"/>leſs than a ſtock of holy Graces can put them into a poſture for it. It's true, <hi>Diogenes,</hi> when he was asked, what be gained by his Philoſophy, anſwered, that he gained this by it, that he was
<hi>ad omnem fortunam paratus,</hi> ready for every thing that ſhould fall out. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy may pretend to this, but nothing but true Chriſtianity can effect it; it is an eaſy matter to ſpeak finely, and ſay, as one did,
<hi>Si fractus illabatur Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, impavidum ferient Ruinae;</hi> if the broken World fall about our Ears, the Ruins of it ſhall not ſtartle us: But nothing leſs than Gracious and Divine Principles can enable a Man piouſly to ſuffer for the Cauſe of God and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; he, that parts with all outward things here, had need have an intereſt in Him, who is better than all: He, that ſtands faſt in a Storm of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without, had need of a pure ſerene Conſcience within; He that will adhere to perſecuted Truth, had need to be well
<pb facs="tcp:60575:4"/>ſetled in it, and carry the ſweet ſavor of it upon his heart: He, that will ſtand out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Threatnings of Men, had need be well-fixed in the Promiſes of God, &amp; from thence draw out Comfort in an Evil Day How can a Chriſtian part with the preſent World, if he hath not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a better, to go to; or lay down a Temporal Life, if he hath not a lively hope of an Eternal one in Heaven? How can he lift up himſelf above the Dregs of a Corrupt World, if he be not extaſied and rap't up in Love to God: or bear the Terrors and Cruelties of Men, if the fear of God do not prevail and over-rule his heart? Humility muſt make him a Worm, a Nothing in his own Eyes, that he may be willing to be trampled on by Men. Obedience muſt work him to a compliance with God's Commanding Will, that Patience may fit him to ſubject to his diſpoſing one. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, it is a great, an Heroical thing, to ſuffer for Religion; it muſt be Grace,
<pb facs="tcp:60575:4"/>true Grace, (ſuch as carries a man up above himſelf and the World, and joins him to the Fountain of Comfort and Happineſs) that will make him fit to ſuffer and loſe all for Righteouſneſs ſake.</p>
            <p>Reader, The enſuing Diſcourſe hath no other deſign, but only to ſhew, how Chriſtians are to bear Sufferings, and what Graces are requiſite thereunto: If any Glory may come to God, or Profit to Men by it, it is as much as is deſired by him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Lover of Truth, <hi>Edw. Polhil.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:60575:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60575:5"/>
            <hi>ARMAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RA DEI:</hi> OR, A Preparation for ſuffering in an Evil-day.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Perſecution will come on good men. This World is mixt of Comforts and Sorrows. The old enmity will perſecute. Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Saints will ſhew it ſelf inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and outwardly. The Church is heir to the Croſs. God orders Sufferings for good. Things abroad and at home admoniſh us.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ONe Apoſtle tells us. That <hi>all that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Another acquaints us, That this <hi>is no ſtrange thing;</hi> A third wiſhes us, not <hi>to marvel at the Worlds</hi> hatred. Its true, the Sufferings
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60575:6"/>of good men have been an old Stumbling-block.
<hi>Pompey</hi> complained, that Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was very dark: The Poet was ready to think that there were no Gods: Nay, the holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> cried out, <hi>I have cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my heart in vain;</hi> as if Religion were to no purpoſe: Yet, if we conſider all, thoſe Sufferings are not to be wondred at.</p>
            <p>This World ſtanding between Heaven and Hell, muſt partake of both: Heaven is all comfort; Hell is all miſery: The middle World muſt have a mixture; here evil men may meet with Comforts, and good men may meet with Afflictions.</p>
            <p>The old Enmity between the Seed of the Serpent, and the Seed of the Woman will ſtir up Perſecution to the Worlds end. <hi>He that is born after the fleſh, will perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him that is born after the Spirit:</hi> Tis his nature and property to do ſo; a thing no more to be wondred at than the ſtinging of a Serpent, or the tearing of a Briar. Many pretences were made to palliate the Perſecution of the primitive Chriſtians. Under <hi>Trajan</hi> it was ſaid, That the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were too numerous; under <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> it was given out, That all kinds of Penal Evils came for their ſakes; under <hi>Severus</hi> it was alleaged, That they were guilty of all kind of Villanies; under <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60575:6"/>it was fairly pretended, That there muſt be but one Religion in the Empire; But in truth all theſe were but ſo many colours, the venome of the Serpent was at the root; the devilliſh Enmity, which is in carnal men againſt the Saints, was the very proper cauſe of all thoſe Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Wickedneſs will proceed from the wicked; the old Enmity will breake out, and that not only in men groſly wicked, but in fair Moraliſts too. A <hi>Trajan</hi> or <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus</hi> can perſecute, as well as a <hi>Nero:</hi> The ſame root of bitterneſs is in all carnal men.</p>
            <p>The inherent Corruption in the Saints will ſhew it ſelf inwardly and outwardly: Inwardly it will raiſe up a Proſecution in their own Boſome; <hi>the Fleſh luſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spirit.</hi> No ſooner is the New-Creature born, but the indwelling Sin doth hunt it as a <hi>Partridge upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> and ſeeks the life of its Infant-gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as
<hi>Herod</hi> did the life of Chriſt in the Cradle. And how can the Saints wonder at a Perſecution without, when they have one within in their Souls? Or how can they expect leſs than Briars in the world, when they feel a Thorn in their own fleſh? Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly it will, even in Saints, when let out, be injurious to others. A <hi>David,</hi> when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60575:7"/>his Corruption breaks forth, can be inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane towards the <hi>Ammonites;</hi> an <hi>Aſa</hi> can impriſon the Seer, and oppreſs the People. And if Corruption may do ſo in a Saint, in whom it is in part mortified, what may it not doe in a Son of <hi>Belial,</hi> in whom it is the total ruling Principle? In the one, the regenerate part holds back; but in the other, the whole Soul is carried out to wickedneſs. It is no wonder that ſuch an one ſhould perſecute; his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are entirely for it.</p>
            <p>The Church is Heir to the Croſs. It's ſuffering began from the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> and hath continued everſince. <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods peculiar People was firſt oppreſſed in <hi>Egypt,</hi> under cruel Bondage; then vexed in <hi>Canaan</hi> by the neighbour Nations round about them; after wards carried captive into <hi>Babylon,</hi> and at laſt trod under foot by <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes.</hi> The Chriſtian Church was firſt perſecuted by the Pagan Emperors; then torn in pieces by <hi>Arians</hi> and other Hereticks; afterwards over-run with <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> and at laſt trod down by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> All along it hath been in a ſuffering condition, and it is no wonder, if it ſuffer on till it come to reſt in Heaven.</p>
            <p>God orders the ſufferings of the Church
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60575:7"/>for his own glory, and his Peoples good. He orders them for his own glory; Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is admirable in preſerving a ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church. The Ark ſloats upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and drowns not; the Buſh burns, and is not conſumed; the Lilly is among Thornes, and withers not; the Saints are perplexed but not in deſpair; perſecuted but not forſaken; caſt down but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. Strength comes forth out of weakneſs; Light ariſes out of darkneſs; the Bones, though ſometimes dry and hopeleſs, live; the Witneſſes are ſlain and revive again; Preſſures multiply the Church, and Sufferings propagate it; And what a ſight is this? Who may think much at thoſe Sufferings, in which ſo much of God appears? Again he orders them for his Peoples good; the Fann will purge away their Vanity; the Furnace will melt out their Droſs; every Name of Perſecution will lift them up neerer to Heaven; their Sufferings will make them white; their Graces will come forth as Gold out of the fire in their pure Luſtre; the Rod will bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and bring forth peacable fruit of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; the holy Spirit will come down upon them in larger effuſions of Grace and Comfort: And what things are theſe? Who can imagine thoſe Sufferings needleſs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60575:8"/>which have ſo excellent an iſſue?</p>
            <p>To conclude; Things abroad and at home admoniſh us: Abroad, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion runs very low; Idolatry growes in the world, and where that goes before, Cruelty follow's after: The fiery Furnace waits upon the Idol; the Scarlet Whore, full of Fornications, will drink the blood of Saints; the falſe Worſhippers will perſecute the true; the Sighs and Groans of the poor Souls in <hi>France</hi> do alarm all that have any ſenſe of Piety or Humanity: Who can but mourn at ſuch mourning Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences? At home our ſins are grown up to Heaven; Oaths, Blaſphemies, Perjuries, Helliſh Plots, Uncleanneſſes Exceſſes, A the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, Contempt of Ordinances, Deadneſs and Formality in Religion, Unthankfulneſs and Unſaithfulneſs to God, are found among us. The Cloud of Guilt which hangs over our heads, is very black &amp; ready to come down in Storms of wrath upon us: Sword and Plague and Fire have already conſumed us; and, becauſe we Sin on with a ſtiff neck, heard heart, and impudent face, more Judgments may be expected:
<hi>Eliphas</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wicked taking <hi>root, Suddenly cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Habitation, Job</hi> 5.3. He that ſees our aggravated Sins, may eaſily foretel our ſudden deſtruction.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60575:8"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> It is uſeful to Chriſtians to diſcern the ſigns of the Times, and to be ready for all the Will of God. Providence bids us pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for ſufferings; we have need to do ſo. Suffering is hard to ſenſe, and the excellency of a Chriſtian. The prepared Chriſtian is an happy man, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared miſerable.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>Two things are of great uſe to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; the one is, to diſcern the Signs of the Time. He that looks without and ſees the State of things there, and then turns to Scripture, and there ſees the iſſues that wait upon ſuch States, may diſcern the ſigns of the Time. The Luxury of the old World was a ſign of the Deluge; the Perſecution of the Prophets was a ſign of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Deſolation. When <hi>Epheſus</hi> declined, and left its firſt love, the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick was removing: When
<hi>Laodicea</hi> was luke-warm, God was ready to ſpue them out of his mouth. And ſo it is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things; ſuch and ſuch a State of things will have ſuch and ſuch an iſſue. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of this will make Chriſtians time their duties, and do every thing in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60575:9"/>true ſeaſon of it, which is no leſs profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then beautiful. The other thing is, to be ready for all the Will of God; to have Graces aptly anſwering to Providence: Such holy Joy as may tune the heart to Proſperity; and ſuch humble Submiſſion as may frame the heart to adverſity: This is that bleſſed temper, that bids every thing welcome that comes in the Will of God.</p>
            <p>If we obſerve the ſigns of our Times, we may eaſily diſcern Judgments a coming, and therefore nothing can be more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than to prepare for Sufferings. God hath a controverſy with us, and ſeems to ſpeak to us by his Providence, as he did to <hi>Iſrael</hi> by his Prophet,
<hi>Prepare to meet thy God.</hi> Sit down then, O Chriſtians, and conſider how to do it, and think with your ſelves, with what penitential Tears, Wreſtling, Supplications, real Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and holy Reſignations you will meet with him. Jeſus Chriſt <hi>the Captain of your ſalvation,</hi> ſeems now to ask you by his Providence, as the Roman General did his Souldiers, <hi>Are you ready?</hi> Reflect upon your ſelves, and conſider; are you ready to keep the Word of Chriſts Patience, to take up his Croſs and follow him? Though the croſs be not yet upon your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60575:9"/>backs, yet you muſt carry it in your Hearts; your minds muſt be ready at his call to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any thing, rather than to part with the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Preparation is neceſſary to every good work. The Pagan Prieſts had preparatory Waſhings before the ſacrifice; the People had an <hi>hoc age</hi> cried to them to awaken their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. The Jewes were to waſh their Clothes at the giving of the Law; they had their Preparations to Sabbaths and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Chriſtians are to prepare for the Wood and for the holy Table; but above all, Preparation is neceſſary to ſufferings. The greater the thing is, the more requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite is the Preparation: Suffering is a great thing, hard to Senſe, harſh to Fleſh and Blood. It may be it takes away the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goods which are dear to men; it may be it comes neerer, and touches the Bone and the Fleſh, which is dearer then out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things: It may be it goes further, and treads down the precious Life, which is highly valuable. Nature in the beſt, ſhrinks and flies away from ſuch things as theſe; and, ſupernatural Graces and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances lift up men above themſelves, they will never bear them. In ſuch a caſe as this we have need to put on all our Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Armor; not this or that piece only, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60575:10"/>all of it; and not only to put it on, but to gird it on too: All will be little enough to make us ſtand in the evil day. Again, the more excellent a thing is, the more requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite is the Preparation: Suffering for Chriſt is the excellency of a Chriſtian, the top and Complement of all his Graces; Faith cannot riſe higher; Love cannot ſhew it ſelf better than in this: No Profeſſion of Chriſtianity is ſo high, nor Imitation of Chriſt ſo full, as that which is made in blood: Here is the Chriſtians <hi>conſummatum eſt;</hi> his work is done, and Heaven opens to receive him into glory: And how ſhould we prepare our Souls, and gird up the Loins of our Minds, that we may be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that which is the higheſt Stature of a Chriſtian in this World, and the neereſt capacity to a better?</p>
            <p>This Preparation is of very great moment to Chriſtians: Upon their having, or not having of it, depends their Happineſs or Miſery.</p>
            <p>He that is prepared for Sufferings, come what will come, is a happy man; if ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings do not come, he is yet a Martyr in mind and purpoſe. God ſees the ſuffering frame that is in him; his willing mind is accepted as much as if his blood were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Shed; and being ready to dye for Chriſt,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60575:10"/>he is ready to live with him in Heaven; If Sufferings come, he is provided for then. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ready to be bound and die for the name of Jeſus. <hi>Polycarpe,</hi> when threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Various deaths, made this reply, <hi>Quid tardas?</hi> Why doſt thou delay? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict what thou wilt. The prepared Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is ready for all the Will of God, which is an happineſs that no Suffering can inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt: He is in a poſture to overcome all the World, and he will do it. The very Pagan Emperors did obſerve the primitive mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs to be Victors in death. It is ſaid of the Martyr <hi>Vincentius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. cent. 4. cap.
12.</note> that according to his name, he overcame in Words, and overcame in Puniſhments; overcame in Confeſſion, and overcame in Tribulation; overcame in Fire, and over came in Water; overcame Living and overcame Dying. The prepared Chriſtian is a <hi>Vincent,</hi> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer of the World; his Love is above the ſmiles of it, his Fear above the Terrors of it: Nay, <hi>he is more than a Conqueror;</hi> he overcomes by ſuffering, and lives by death; nay <hi>being dead, he yet ſpeaks</hi> forth the truth he ſuffered for, and propagates it to all poſterity: Neither need we wonder at this Conqueſt, he is not alone but hath God with him: And, as the Emperor <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus Verus</hi> ſaid of the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60575:11"/>
               <hi>He carries God about with him in conſcience;</hi> and where God is, there muſt be happineſs in the moſt afflicted Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the whole ſacred Trinity are preſent with him; the everlaſting Father will ſtrengthen him; the Son will walk with him in the fiery Furnace; the holy Spirit will come to him with all his cordials.
<hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> was never ſo full of it as when he was ſtoned.<note place="margin">Hiſt. mag. Cent. 2.</note> The Martyr <hi>Felicitas</hi> profeſſed to her Perſecutor, That ſhe had the holy Spirit in her: The prepared Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hath a Spirit of Power in Infirmities, a Spirit of Glory in Reproaches, a Spirit of Comfort in Diſtreſſes. There are no ſuch rich Anointings, as thoſe that wait upon the Croſs of Chriſt: At other times a Chriſtian hath ſome meaſures of the Spirit; but then he hath ſuch large ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions of it, that no Sufferings can make him miſerable: The Clouds without can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not break the ſerenity in his Conſcience; the noiſe of a troubleſome World cannot interrupt that Divine Peace which keeps his heart; no malice of man can hinder the ſheddings of Gods Love into him; no wants or exigencies can deprive him of the hidden Manna promiſed to the Overcomer; he is happy even in a Vale of Tears: And what will he be in Heaven? There his reward
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60575:11"/>will be great, nay, greater than that of others.</p>
            <p>On the other hand; he that is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for Sufferings, is a miſerable man: He hath a Name of Religion and that's all; a Notion of the Goſpel, but without a Root; he hath a falſe Chriſt, that is, a Chriſt without a Croſs, but the right Chriſt he knowes not; a pretence to Heaven he hath, but he is not in a poſture for it, neither will he go thither in an hard way: If Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings come, he is ſnared, as Fiſhes in an evil Net; the ſurprize will rob him of that which he ſeems to have; he will not have ſo much as the Name or notion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion left: Chriſt will be an Offence, or ſtumbling-Block to him; Heaven it ſelf will not be worth ſuffering for. Thus thoſe of the Stony ground received the word with joy, but becauſe their hearts were not ready for it, as ſoon as Perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe, they were offended.<note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. Cent. 2. cap. 3.</note> Thus it was obſerved among the Primitive Chriſtians, that the unready and unprepared did faint and fall in time of Perſecution. The Cup of Sufferings is bitter, Nature ſtarts at it: The unprepared Chriſtian, rather than drink it, will in all likelihood turn Apoſtate in the day of trial; proſperous error will be embraced by him before per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60575:12"/>Truth; Idolatary with the World will goe down better than the pure Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip without it; Chriſt coming in Poverty and Tribulation will be forſaken; Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt appearing in the Pomp and outward greatneſs of the World, will be followed: Meer Vanity will outweigh all the great offers of the Goſpel; a Soul and a God will be laid at ſtake for a little outward proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: And what a forlorn Condition is this? And without Repentance, how diſmal muſt the end be? The Good God, whom he hath forſaken, will depart from him; Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour will caſt him out; a curſe &amp; a blaſt will be upon his Proſperity; a ſting and a wound in Conſcience will make him weary of himſelf; in a word, he will become loathſome to God, Men, and himſelf.<note place="margin">Cypr. de Lapſis.</note> It is ſtoried, That in the third Century the tokens of Gods wrath came in an extraordinary way upon thoſe Chriſtians that fell off in time of Perſecution; ſome of them were ſtruck dumb, ſome vexed with Devils, ſome tormented in their bowels unto Death; and, though not in theſe wayes, yet in other will his wrath come down upon all Apoſtates; if they are not dumb before men, they will be ſpeechleſs before God; if Devils vex not their Bodies, they will yet poſſeſs their Souls; if there
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60575:12"/>be no torments in their Bowels, yet there are in their Conſciences: The miſeries, which Apoſtates incur, are much greater than thoſe, which they avoid by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacies. It is therefore highly reaſonable, that we ſhould prepare for Sufferings, leſt by Apoſtacy we make our ſelves more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, than any outward Suffering can make us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Preparation for Sufferings conſidered more generally. A Chriſtian that will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for Sufferings muſt ſecure to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf three things; that is, A good Cauſe, a good Heart, and a good God.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>Having ſeen the neceſſity of Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the neceſſity of Preparation, I come now to the main thing intended; to conſider how a Chriſtian may be prepared for Sufferings: And here I ſhall firſt ſpeak in General, and then more Particularly. In General, a Chriſtian, that would be prepared for Sufferings, muſt ſecure to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf three things; a good Cauſe, a good Heart, and a good God; The firſt will make Suffering honourable; the Second will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60575:13"/>make us us meet for it; the third will give aſſiſtance and comfort in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Chriſtian muſt ſecure to himſelf a good Cauſe; he muſt take care not to ſuffer as an Evil doer; this is not grateful to God, nor honorable among Men; in it Chriſt is not imitated, but Chriſtianity is ſhamed: Such Sufferers are the Devils Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; it cannot be reaſonably expected that they ſhould have the gratious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, or any comfort in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; their own hearts cry out, Guilty, and plainly tel them, that their Suffering is but the juſt wages of their Iniquity. A Chriſtian muſt be ſure, that there be no guilt in that which he ſuffers for. Holy <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Innocency was found in him, Dan.</hi> 6.22. He ſpeaks not of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of his Perſon, as if he were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin; but of the innocency of his Cauſe, for which he ſuffered: His praying againſt a Law did not merit a Den of Lions; he broke the Humane Command only to keep the Divine. It highly concerns the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to have an innocent Cauſe; it is the Cauſe, not the meer Suffering, that makes the Martyr. Again, the Chriſtian muſt take care, that he ſuffer not as a Buſy-body in other mens Matter; he muſt not have his own Station, nor forfeit Gods protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60575:13"/>he muſt abide with God in his Calling, and do his own Buſineſs. God took care of the Bird ſitting over her young in her Neſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.6. but not of the wandring one. The learned
<hi>Johannes Fancius,</hi> of a Miniſter of the Goſpel in his Prince's Court, turned Miniſter of State to his Prince, and was at laſt for ſome evil Counſel, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to dye; and before he ſuffered, he much lamented the leaving of his Calling, and left this Diſtick.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Diſce meo exemplo mandato munere fungi,</l>
               <l>Et fuge ceu peſtem <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Learn this of me, thine own Office to bear,</l>
               <l>In others meddle not, the Plague is there.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is very uncomfortable to a Chriſtian, when he runs into Sufferings by going out of his own Sphear. Moreover, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an muſt take care, that he ſuffer not for his own raſhneſs. He that defaced the Emperors Edict againſt Chriſtians, and Suffered for it, was not accounted a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. Biſhop <hi>Audas</hi> demoliſhed the Perſian Temple, dedicated to the Fire, as their <hi>Numen,</hi> and ſuffered for it; but it was reckoned as a Piece of raſh and unreaſonable Zeal: We muſt not caſt our ſelves into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; God will keep us in our ways,<note place="margin">Theod. Hiſt. Lib. 4, cap. 39.</note> not in our Precipices. We muſt take up the Croſs that God makes for us, but not make
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60575:14"/>one of our ſelves by our own raſhneſs: If we muſt ſuffer, let it be for that good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is a continual Feaſt; for that Righteouſneſs which is in Conjunction with Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt: Let it be for that Jeſus who ſuffered for us; for that God who crowns momentary Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with eternal Glory. This was the caſe of the Primitive Chriſtians; they ſuffered, but it was in a good Cauſe.
<hi>Juſtin</hi> Martyr and <hi>Athenagoras</hi> in their Apologies for them, ſhew, That there was nothing amiſs found in them; no Atheiſm, no
<hi>Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtean</hi> Suppers, no unclean Copulations, no unjuſt Actions; the only Crime was Chriſtianity. And afterwards <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſhews, That the name in Chriſtians was condemned, but no Crime was found in them towards God or man. This is the firſt thing we are to do, we muſt ſecure a good Cauſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt ſecure good Hearts. It is ſaid of the Children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> that <hi>being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and carrying Bows,</hi> they <hi>turned back in the day of Battel, Pſal.</hi> 78.9. and the reaſon of this we have in the precedent Verſe, they <hi>ſet not their hearts aright.</hi> Unleſs the Heart be good, as well as the Cauſe, men will turn back from God, and the pure Religion: Corrupt Hearts will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60575:14"/>fall in with the World, and ever be on the Sunny ſide: In <hi>Diocleſian's</hi> time they can be Pagans; in
<hi>Conſtantine's</hi> Chriſtians; in <hi>Conſtantius</hi>'s Arrians; in
<hi>Julian's</hi> Pagans again.<note place="margin">Purpuram colunt, non Deum.</note> It is the good Heart only that is ſit for Sufferings. Now two things are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to make a good Heart; it muſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from ſin; and again, it muſt be furniſhed with principles of Grace. 1. It muſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from ſin; from the guilt and power of it: It muſt be purged from the guilt of ſin. A man that hath inward wounds is unfit to bear out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ones. Guilt upon Conſcience, like a Boyl upon the Back, makes one uncapable to bear the burden of a Croſs. They, that are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſts Sufferings in Martyrdome, had need firſt partake of them for Remiſſion: They, that waſh their Robes in the Blood of the Lamb, by ſuffering for him, had need firſt waſh their Conſciences in it to take away their Guiltneſs. It is not imaginable that a man can piouſly embrace a Temporal Death, when immediately after it he ſhall fall into an Eternal one: Or that he can patiently bear the wrath of Man, when the wrath of God is to enſue upon it. It was a very forlorn Caſe with the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> when they were drowning in the Sea, and God looked through the Cloud upon them; and ſo it will be with Chriſtians, if the World be as a troubled Sea to them and withal;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60575:15"/>God look with an angry Face upon them: Therefore it much concernes them to get a pardon ſealed in the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, that, when they come to ſuffer, they may have nothing to bear but the ſingle Croſs, without any preſſure of Guilt upon Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to aggravate it. Again, It muſt be purged from the power of Sin. Every Luſt is a <hi>Dalilah,</hi> an <hi>Exhauſter</hi> (as the Hebrew word ſignifies,) it takes away the Heart, drains and debaſes the man, makes him vile and impotent, and by conſequence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together uncapable of ſo heroical a thing as ſuffering for God is: He that hath ſin reigning in his Heart, will comply with it reigning in the World; he that carrieth an Idol within will fall down to an outward one: Such an one will do any thing rather than ſuffer; The power of ſin muſt be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that a man may be ready to take up the Croſs. Further, the Heart, that it may be good, muſt not only be purged from ſin, but furniſhed with Principles of Grace. The old Heart will not Hear, or Pray, or give Almes, or do any thing for God in a right manner, much leſs will it ſuffer for him. A man muſt have gracious Principles, ſuch as holy Knowledg, Faith, Fear, Love Zeal, Hope, Humility, Obedience, and Patience are, that he may be ready for ſuffering. There is a double preparation for it, Habitual and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60575:15"/>Actual; Habitual ſtands in the having thoſe principles, and actual in the uſing of them. He that hath them hath a Divine temper diſpoſing him for every piece of the Divine Will; he is in the frame of his Heart above Creatures, and hath no Center but in his Creator; he is higher than Time and this lower World, and lies upon the Borders of Heaven and Eternity: His great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns are not in the Smiles and Frowns of men, but in the Will and Favour of God; His fear is of greater evil than the World can inflict; and his expectation is of greater good than the World can beſtow: His Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples make him habitually ready for Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and when occaſion comes, the uſe of them will make him actually ſo. Such an one may ſay at the fiery Trial, as the famous <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prage</hi> did when the Wood was laid to him, <hi>Salve feſta dies,</hi> Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thou joyful day of ſuffering for Chriſt. This is the ſecond thing, we muſt ſecure good Hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt ſecure a good God to be with us in our Sufferings. A good Cauſe will not bear us up without a good Heart, nor will a good Heart ſtand without a good God to ſupport it. The prayer of
<hi>David</hi> is very remarkable, <hi>Let Integrity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs preſerve me, for I wait on thee,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60575:16"/>Pſal.</hi> 25.21. Integrity is a Preſervative; but we muſt wait on God to have our very Integrity preſerved; and pray, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> doth in the precedent Verſe, <hi>O keep my ſoul;</hi> the moſt upright ſoul needs it. Graces keep the Heart, but thoſe very Graces muſt be kept by the <hi>Keeper of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> The God of Grace is as neceſſary to the New-creature as the God of Nature is to the Old: If he withdraw, Faith will fail, Love will cool, Hope will wither, Zeal will be extinct, and all Graces will Vaniſh, as the
<hi>Beams</hi> do upon the abſence of the Sun; The gracious preſence of God is neceſſary to us at all times, eſpecially in times of Suffering.
<hi>Joſeph's</hi> Priſon would have been very diſmal, if God had not been there. When all men forſook <hi>Paul,</hi> he had been very forlorn if God had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him too. How hard is it to be in wants, if the All-ſufficient one be gone? How in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable are Diſtreſſes, if the God of all Comfort be abſent? How ſhall we bear the Cruelties of men if the Father of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies do not aſſiſt us? Or how ſhall we ſtand under own Creature-weakneſs, if the never fainting Creator do not ſtrengthen us? What ſhall we do in doubts if the only Wiſe one do not guide us? Or what ſhall we do in the Vally of the Shadow of death
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60575:16"/>if the living God be not with us? <hi>The Preſence of God</hi> (ſaith a worthy Divine) <hi>will turn a Priſon into a Pallace, a Fiery Furnace into a Gallery of Pleaſure, and the Stocks into a Muſick-School.</hi> Acts 16.25. I may add, it is in ſtead of all things to us: With it no Suffering can be too heavy; without it none can be tolerable. Let us therefore labour to ſecure this Preſence with us, and for that end, let us ſecure our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt, and our walking in him. Firſt let us ſecure our being in Chriſt: God manifeſt in the Fleſh, is the foundation of God sin habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Spirits of men: If Chriſt had not come and mediated for us, God would never have come to dwell and to walk in us: If we are in Chriſt, God, who is perſonally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with his Humane Nature, will be graciouſly preſent with us as Members of of him: We ſhall be preſerved in Chriſt, as pieces of him, by that ſpecial Preſence which accompanies thoſe that are in him. Our bleſſed Saviour prays, that thoſe that were given him might be kept through the Fathers Name, Joh. 17.11. that is, through that Divine Power, Wiſdom, Mercy, and Grace which is with them, Again, let us ſecure our walking in Chriſt. Let us walk after his Command and Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern; that is, in Meekneſs of Wiſdom, in Zeal for Gods Glory, in readineſs of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60575:17"/>in ſweetneſs of Charity, in an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Compliance witht the Divine Will. Let there be ſomewhat of Chriſt in every ſtep, this is the way to have the Divine Preſence with us. Thus our Saviour left us, <hi>If any man Love me he will keep my words, and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our aboad with</hi> him, <hi>Joh.</hi>
14.23. Such as keep his words, ſhall have the <hi>Shechinah,</hi> the Divine Preſence in a peculiar manner with them: This will be to them Joy in Sorrow, Security in Fears Strength in Weakneſs, Life in Death, and All things in the want of All.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Preparation for Suffering; the first dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is, Try thy Heart; ſee the Deceit of it; what Reliques of Sin are there; how it ſteals out of Duties; how falſe it is in Promiſes; how it extenuates Sin: Search &amp; ſee what uprightneſs is there: Doth thy Heart ſet God before thee; doth it reſpect all Commands; doth it eye Gods Glory, and did it make a right contract with Chriſt?</p>
            </argument>
            <p>HAving ſpoke ſomewhat in general touching Preparation for Suffering; I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60575:17"/>now come to ſpeak of it more particularly: And here I ſhall lay down ſeveral Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſhew how a Chriſtian may be in a fit poſture for ſuffering.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we would be in a fit poſture for Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let us diligently try our own Hearts: Suffering is a ſearching thing; it tries a man as fire doth Metals; ſifts and winnowes him as Corn is ſhaken in a Sieve; and diſcovers his thoughts and the bottom of his Heart. Many a man ſeems to be fully for God, yet when the Teſt comes, proves to be for the World: Therefore it is very proper for us, to ſearch our ſelves before hand; to try our Hearts inwardly before the outward trial come; to ſift and winnow our ſelves before Providence do it; to diſcover our Hearts to our ſelves, before God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover them to others: This is Gods own direction to his People; <hi>Gather your ſelves together, yea, gather together O Nation not deſired;</hi> or (as the words in the original may be rendred) <hi>ſearch, lift your ſelves, yea, ſearch, lift your ſelves, O nation not deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, before the Decree bring forth, before the day paſs as the Chaff, before the fierce Anger of the Lord come upon you, before the day of the Lords Anger come upon you,</hi> Zeph. 2.1.2. Approaching Judgments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum us to ſelf examination: Sit down, O
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60575:18"/>Chriſtian, and conſider, what the ſtate of thy Heart is; what of Corruption is there and what of Grace; how much is there for the World, and how much for God; what concupiſcential Strings are there that tie thee to the preſent world, and what An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors caſt in Heaven are there to bear thee up in a Storm; what Chaff or Vanity is there that will go away with every Wind, and what maſſy Grace that will abide the trial: Never is it more neceſſary to deſcend into our ſelves, than in a time of Suffering.</p>
            <p>Search out the Corruption and Deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in thy Heart: If thou wilt believe him that knows the Heart better than it knows it ſelf, <hi>The Heart is deceitful above all things</hi> Jer. 17.9. full of windings and turnings; deceitful beyond its own power of reflection, which, when acted, knows the deceit in part, but cannot dive into the bottom of it. Commune with thine own Heart, O Chriſtian; ask it ſeriouſly, Is there not much Corruption within? are there not reliques of Unbelief, Earthineſs, Senſualneſs, Pride, Hypocricy, Apoſtacy found in thee? Conſider what theſe are; theſe fight under the ſame Colours, and aim at the ſame end with the perſecuting World; theſe would root grace out of thy Heart, as wicked men would root Good out of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60575:18"/>World. As it was with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there went up with them out of <hi>Egypt</hi> a mixed multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which was ready to return again thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo it is with good men, there are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt mixtures in them which would turn back to <hi>Egypt</hi> again: Be not deceived, thy whole entire ſelf is not for ſuffering; the unregenerate part will hang back, and ſay to thee, as Satan in <hi>Peter</hi> did to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Master, Spare thy ſelf:</hi> When dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers approach, the Fleſh will cry out, Oh, Spare thy Eſtate Spare thy Relations, Spare thy Life, why ſhouldeſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf? Take notice therefore, that there is a Traitor in thine own boſom, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou watch, will like the Idolaters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Heart, turn thee aſide from God. Again, ask thy Heart, Doth it not Steal out of holy duties? When thou art a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holy Word, will not thy Heart go out to worldly objects? When thou art joyning with others in Prayer, do not thy thoughts rove up and down about Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal things? If thy Heart be a little elevated towards Heaven, doth it not immediately fall down again? If it be a little inflamed towards God, doth it not inſtantly cool a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? Think with thy ſelf; that Heart, that ſteals away from Duties in which there is nothing grevious to the Body, will be ready to ſteal away from Sufferings which grate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60575:19"/>upon the Fleſh and Senſe: Thou hadſt need to get thy Heart fixed on God in Duties, that when thou comeſt to Suffering, thou myeſt not ſtart away from him. Further yet, ask thy heart; Hath it not been falſe in Vows and Promiſes of better obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and thoſe made at Sacraments or upon Sick-beds? Is not thy Goodneſs as a morning Cloud, and thy life a vain circle of commiſſions of Sin and Confeſſions? And canſt thou truſt ſuch an Heart as this? Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelf, that an Heart, which is falſe in Promiſes, will not be true in Sufferings; that goodneſs that paſſes away like the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dew at other times, will utterly vaniſh when a ſcorching Perſecution comes: Learn therefore to be true in Promiſes, that thou mayſt be true in Suffering; get ſuch a real Goodneſs as may abide the trial in an Evil day. Moreover, ask thy ſelf one queſtion more, Cannot thy Heart colour over evil things? Is it not apt to extenuate ſin and ſay, It is but a little one; to make nothing of idle Words or petty Oaths? And what may not ſuch an Heart do to avoid Sufferings? May it not put a fair gloſs upon Popery it ſelf, and ſay, the Papiſts have the ſubſtance of Religion, and why ſhould we ſcruple humane Rights and Ceremonies? They have the ſacred Scriptures, and why ſhould we ſtumble at ſuperfluous Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60575:19"/>Their Images are not the terminative object of Worſhip, but the motive only; and why may we not uſe Humane Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to move us to Devotion? Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf is but a kind of nicety, they ſay, the body of Chriſt is in the Euchariſt after the maner of Spirits; we ſay,<note place="margin">Bellar. de Euch. Lib. 1 ca. 2. Lib 3. cap.
4.</note> that it is there Spiritually: And how little doth the difference ſeem to be? Praying to Saints and Angels is but a vanity, a void thing: Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane merit is an harmleſs thing, if it be grafted upon Chriſt and the Promiſe: The Pope himſelf is a Biſhop, and what need we think him Antichriſt? The falſe heart can paint the Whore in every part, and make her look as if ſhe were not <hi>Mystery, Babilon, the Mother of Harlots &amp; Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Earth.</hi> Labour then to know more and more of the deceitfulneſs of thy heart, that it may not cheat thee in times of Perſecution: He that truſts in his heart is a Fool, nay a ſecret Idolater; let us car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an holy jealouſy over our hearts: The Carnal heart will preſume, but knows not its own weakneſs; it will promiſe much, but perform little or nothing. <hi>Peter</hi> was in a very high ſtrain,
<hi>though all men be offended, yet will not I,</hi> Matth. 26.33. And again,
<hi>though I ſhould die with thee, yet will I not deny thee,</hi> Verſe 35. But alas he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60575:20"/>was herein (as <hi>Forus</hi> obſerves) but a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of thoſe that lean upon their own Free-will;<note place="margin">Ecce columna fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſima ad unius aurae impulſum tota con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremuit; ubi eſt illa pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittentis audacia, &amp; deſe pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumentis? <hi>Auſt. in Joh. Tract. 11 3.</hi>
               </note> he knew too little of himſelf, preſumed too much upon his own power, and fell miſerably in the denial of his Lord: This great Pillar fel before the breath of a poor Damſel; his Confidence and Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proved but a meer Vanity; Do not, O Chriſtian, think thy ſelf better than this great Apoſtle; ſtudy thine own heart, and ſee the Corruption there, that thou maieſt not fall by preſumption; but ſtand in the Power of his Grace, who is able to confirm thee to the end.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Search thy heart and ſee what upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is there; thou haſt a name, a notion of Religion, a form of Godlineſs; but haſt thou the thing, the truth of grace, the power of Religion in thy heart? It is grace, true grace that muſt eſtabliſh the heart <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.9. It is <hi>Gold tried in the fire Revel.</hi> 3.18. that is, <hi>pure grace,</hi> that muſt <hi>endure the fiery trial.</hi> Conſider thy ſelf, O Chriſtian, Is there any true integrity in thee? Where are the Marks and Caracters of it appearing in thee? Put Interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to thine own heart; Doſt thou indeed ſet the Lord alwaies before thee? Doſt thou do every thing as in his Preſence and under his Eye? This is very comfortable;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60575:20"/>he that truly walks with God in other things, will through grace walk with him in Sufferings too: He that hath an holy reſpect to Gods Preſence and Eye at other times, will have ſo in a time of Trial alſo. The Conſtancy of God's People ſet forth in
<hi>Pſalm</hi> 44. is very obſervable; they were given as <hi>Sheep for meat,</hi> ſold <hi>for nought,</hi> made <hi>a reproach,</hi> and <hi>a ſcorne, a by-word,</hi> and <hi>a ſhaking of the head among the people;</hi> yet their heart was <hi>not turned back,</hi> neither did their
<hi>ſteps decline from Gods ways,</hi> Verſe 18. They were <hi>broken in the place of Dragons, covered in the ſhadow of Death:</hi> Yet they did not
<hi>forget the name of</hi> their <hi>God, nor ſtretch out their hands to</hi> a ſtrang God, <hi>Verſe</hi> 20. And whence was this cloſe adherence unto God? The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is rendred in the 21th. <hi>Verſe;</hi> if they ſhould forſake God, he would <hi>ſearch</hi> them <hi>out, for he knoweth the ſecrets of the heart:</hi> We ſee how they were affected with the Preſence and All-ſeing Eye of God, and how doth it affect us? If it make us depart from other ſins, it will much more make us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from ſo great a ſin as Apoſtacy is. Again art thou true in thy active obedience to God? Haſt thou an univerſal reſpect to all the Commands, even to thoſe that call for right Hands and right Eyes? This is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60575:21"/>very well; he that is true in active obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, will be ſo in paſſive; he that is for all the Commands of God, will be for the Command of taking up the Croſs, and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for Chriſt. The Commands are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulative, one of them is linked to another; the ſtamp of Divine Authority is upon all; the Glory of God is concerned in all; they are all united in the root of Charity. Thoſe Principles of Grace which prompt to the obedience of one, will prompt to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of all: He that is ſincere in doing, will be ſincere in ſuffering. Further, haſt thou a ſingle Eye, a pure intention at the great end? is it thy real aim that God in all things may be glorified? This is a good Sign; he that hath a ſingle Eye in one thing, will have it in another; he that glorifies God in other things, will glorify him in ſufferings too. A man is as his end is; what the forme is in Naturals, that the end is in Morals: He, that hath God for his Center and ultimate end, will embrace all the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums that tend thither, and Suffering as the higheſt Medium of all; therein is the higheſt Love demonſtrated, and God is practically lifted up above all; his glory is upon the Throne, and Eſtates, Relations Lives; all Earthly Concerns are at the Foot-ſtool: Let us ſet our hearts upon the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60575:21"/>great end, that, whether we be doing Gods Commanding Will, or ſuffering under his Diſpoſing one, the great deſign of God's glory may be ſtill carried on by us. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, ask thy ſelf, what was thy origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal contract with Jeſus Chriſt? How and upon what terms didſt thou eſpouſe him? Didſt thou take him entirely as he is offered in the Goſpel? Diſt thou take him, Croſs and all? Diſt thou ſit down and count what Chriſtianity might coſt thee? It may be thou mayſt be called to part with all, to hate Father, Mother, Wife, Children, Life it ſelf for Chriſt: Diſt thou deliberately conſider theſe things, and yet piouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, that thou wouldſt have Chriſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he coſt thee? this is very excellent, thou art now a Martyr in purpoſe,<note place="margin">Veniant crux, ignis, oſſium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractiones, modo Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Said <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </note> and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually haſt ſwallowed down all the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that go along with the Goſpel: When the Croſs comes thou wilt take it up upon thy back: The fleſh poſſibly may murmure; but thou wilt ſay, this was my original con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract with Chriſt; theſe were the terms of my Eſpouſals: I accept the Croſs, and will follow my ſuffering Saviour; he is worthy for whom I ſuffer, and the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are not worthy to be compared with the glory to come: Let us therefore be ſure that we have made a right contract with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60575:22"/>Chriſt and accepted him Croſs and all, that when Sufferings come, we may not fall off from him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The ſecond direction for Suffering, Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of ſin; an unmortified man is not in a capacity to ſuffer. We muſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify all ſin, particularly the unbelief of the Heart, the Love of the World in the three great Luſts of it; the Hypocriſy in the Heart, and the vain Superſtition that is there.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>Having diſpatched the firſt Direction, I come to a ſecond: If we would be in a poſture for ſuffering, let us ſeriouſly ſet our ſelves to mortify ſin: There is in Chriſtians a double conformity to Chriſts Death; the one ſtands in the mortification of Sin; our <hi>old man is crucified with him, Rom.</hi> 6.6. dying away by a ſecret virtue from his Croſs: The other ſtands <hi>in bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>Croſs;</hi> thereby we fill up the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24. The Sufferings of Chriſt in his Natural Body were full, but the Sufferings of Chriſt in his Myſtical Body at daily to be filled up: The firſt confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60575:22"/>makes way for the ſecond: The mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of inward Luſts, is an excellent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative to the enduring of outward Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. An unmortified man, that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of his Luſts, is in no fit ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to ſuffer for Chriſt: He is a part of that World that lieth in wickedneſs; the World will love him as a part of it ſelf, and he will comply with the World as a part doth with the whole; a little particle of Water will, if it be poſſible, fall into a round drop, that it may anſwer to the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the great Ocean whereof it is a part; and an unmortified man will be All-amode, and of the ſame figure (be it Pagan or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Idolatry) with the corrupt World, whereof he is a part; his compliance will be ſuch that he will have no occaſion for ſufferings, neither is imaginable for what he will ſuffer from the World: Will he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, as good men do, to avoid that greateſt of evils, Sin? That is it which he allows and indulges in himſelf, that is the darling of his Soul, the joy of his way, the current of his life, the only element in which he converſes, and may he ſuffer to avoid ſuch a thing as that is? Or will he ſuffer to avoid, the greateſt of puniſhments, Hell and Death? No ſurely, in willing his Luſts he virtually wils Hell and the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60575:23"/>of it; in acting his ſin, his feet go down to death, and all the wrath that is to come; Or will he ſuffer for God, out of Love to him, and reſpect to his glory? It is not imaginable, that he ſhould ſuffer for God whom he Serves not, or Love him with the Idol in his heart, or reſpect his glory againſt whom he is in arms, and woſe Laws and honour he treads down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet: Or will he ſuffer or Chriſt his Saviour, who died to waſh away his Sins in his own blood? It is not credible that he ſhould ſuffer for a Chriſt whom he never yet received, or take up the yoke of the croſs when he caſts off the yoke of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; he cannot be ſaved in his ſins, no, not by Chriſt himſelf; the atoning blood will not waſh him that wallows in thoſe corruptions that are the price of it; Or will he ſuffer for the Goſpel; He turns a deaf car to the Calls; violates the ſacred Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, caſts away the pretious offers of it, and it is not to be thought, that he will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for that Goſpel which he ſo deſpiſes. Indeed it would be a very ſtrange thing for him to ſuffer; in ſo doing he muſt part with all this World in which his portion &amp; total ſum of happineſs lies; he muſt ſuffer the ſpoyling of his goods when he hath no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euring ſubſtance in Heaven; be a reproach
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60575:23"/>among men when he hath no honor with God; and caſt away a temporal life when he hath no title to an eternal one. We ſee by theſe things that an unmortified man is not in caſe to ſuffer for Chriſt. Awake therefore O Chriſtian, ſet upon the work of Mortification; reſiſt inward Corruptions that thou maieſt ſtand againſt outward temptations, lay holy reſtraints upon ſin that thou maieſt bear a Guiſon for Chriſt; die unto ſin that thou maieſt be able to die for the Goſpel; ſet thy heart againſt every thing of Concupiſcence that breaths in thee, that there may be nothing to turn thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from the ſure Religion; caſt out every ſecret idol out of thine heart, that thou maiſt not fall down and worſhip the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Idols in the World: Do this work im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially, do not mortify one or two ſins, but all: Every indulged Luſt is a Traitor in thy boſome, a falſe Byas upon thy heart, Spare it not. But to give ſome particular inſtances labor to mortify the ſins follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mortify the unbelief in thy heart: This is the foundation of Apoſtacy,<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>22</hi> qu. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> the greateſt of ſins, becauſe the greateſt ſeparation from God, it
<hi>dep irts from the living God,</hi> Hebr. 3.12. it <hi>gives the lie to the true God,</hi> 1, Joh. 5.10. it blaſts the pretious Goſpel,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60575:24"/>as if it were not worthy to be obeyed in its Precepts, or credited in its Myſteries or promiſes. If it totally prevail in the heart, there can be no ſuch thing as ſuffering for Religion. To ſuch an unbeliever Chriſt is but a Fancy, and the Goſpel but a golden dream, for which ſuffering is plainly ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous; and if it be in thy heart but in ſome degree, it will in the ſame degree weaken thee and make thee ready to ſtagger at the Croſs: Watch therefore over the unbelief in thy boſom; aſſure thy ſelf of this, that which inwardly departs from God will be ready to depart from him outwardly too; that which Secretly gives him the lie will be ready to deny him openly when ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing comes: Look narrowly to thy heart, if there ariſe there Scruples touching the Myſteries or Promiſes of the Goſpel, bid them be gone, drive them out of thy heart in the power of the word; theſe come to undermine thy Chriſtianity and make thee fall in a day of triall If diſtruſts and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential fears disquiet thee, chide thy baſe heart, charge it to truſt in that God that never leaves thoſe that are his: When thou art ready to ſink in the deep waters, call to thy fearful heart, ask it, why it doubts, the Lord will be with thee to bear thee up in his Arms: When thou ſtarteſt at the fiery
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60575:24"/>Furnace, telthy ſelf, that the Lord will be there in thoſe inward comforts which will make outward torments tolerable; ſet thy heart to hate and extirpate this curſed root of Apoſtacy; expoſt ulate with thy Soul, and ſay, Hath God let down a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Grace and Salvation from Heaven to us, and ſhall it not be believed? Hath he given us the two immutable things, his Word and his Oath, and wilt thou yet be ſuch a wretch as not to believe him? Hath thy Saviour Chriſt ſealed up the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Truth with his own blood, and wilt thou be ſo vile as not to ſeal it up by Faith? Arm and ſtrengthen thy heart againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, that when the trial comes thou maieſt be ready to ſpeak to thy ſoul, as
<hi>Hilarion</hi> did, <hi>egredere, animamea, egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, quid times? quid dubitas?</hi> Go out, my ſoul, Go out, why doſt thou ſear or doubt? Heaven is ready for thee, and great is thy reward there.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mortify the Love of the World, the three great Luſts mentioned 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.16. <hi>the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life,</hi> that is, the inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Love of Senſual Pleaſures, Earthly Riches, and Wordly Honour: Theſe three make the World in the heart, and joyn us to the outward World to become one with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60575:25"/>it; Unleſs theſe Concupiſcential Chains be broken, we can never be in a poſture for ſuffering; if thou wilt not part with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Senſual Pleaſure for Chriſt, thou wilt never ſuffer for him; if Luſt blind thee and turn thee into a Bruit, thou wilt be too low and baſe to be capable of it: He that is mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the fire of Luſt, will not endure the flames of Martyrdome; he that makes his belly his God will never ſuffer to avoid I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry. It is very obſervable in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that firſt he tels them, that <hi>whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and wine,</hi> and <hi>new wine take away the heart. Hos.</hi> 4.11. and then adds, <hi>My People ask counſel at their ſtocks;</hi> that is, their Idols, <hi>Verſe</hi> 12. A Senſual man, that is unhearted by his Luſts, is much fitter to fall down to an Idol, than to ſuffer for Religion. Separate thy ſelf therefore from the ſenſuality of the World, that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt never fall into the Idolatry of it: Put away the Cup of Pleaſures, that thou maieſt be in capacity to drink of the Cup of Sufferings; the Senſual Cup leads to ſtings and torments; but the Suffering one tends to the pure Pleaſures that are above. Again, if thou wilt not part with one earthly Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate for Chriſt, thou wilt never ſuffer for him. When our Saviour bid the young man, ſell all, <hi>he went away ſorrowful,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60575:25"/>Math.</hi> 19.22. <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Facultates ſue velut compedes ligaverunt; illa fuerunt vincula, illae catenae, quibus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus erat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tardata &amp; fides preſſa, &amp; anima vincta. <hi>De lapſis.</hi>
               </note> ſpeaking of ſome in his time that fell off in perſecution, ſaith, <hi>that their eſtates were as chains and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to them; that they could not go and ſuffer for Chriſt.</hi> The covetous man, who is a mental Idolater, will, if occaſion require, be an outward one too, and fall down to a Stock or Stone rather than loſe his Land. If thou wouldeſt be able to ſuffer for Chriſt, thou muſt break off the earthly Chains from thy ſoul, that, when the Temptation comes and thou art offered, as the bleſſed Martyr <hi>Julitta</hi> was, to have thy eſtate upon the denial of Chriſt, thou maieſt then be able to give the ſame anſwer as ſhe did,<note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. cent. 4. cap. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Valeat vita, valeant meae facultates;</hi> Farewel life, farewel Eſtate: Take heed that thy poor ſoul do not hang about Houſes and Lands, when thou art called forth to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Chriſt and the pure Religion. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if thou wilt not part with thy worldly honour for Chriſt, thou wilt never fuffer for him: An ambitious man will do any thing for advancement; he will bow to an Idol, that himſelf may be honoured; he lives upon a blaſt, a little popular air, and is too vain and light to ſuffer for Religion; caſt away therefore the love of Mundane Glory, that thou maieſt bear the reproach of Chriſt; humble thy ſelf before God, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60575:26"/>thou maieſt be able to ſuffer for his Truth: Count it an honour to ſuffer ſhame for Chriſt; be willing to be reproached for him who can give thee the Spirit of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Mortify the Hypocriſy that is in thy boſom: This ſin is the art of ſeeming good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or vice in a Vizor: It is by this that men perſonate more grace than they have, and enlarge their forms of Godlineſs beyond the power, and make a profeſſion much greater than is ever filled up: It is from the remnants of this in good men that they ſometimes take falſe ſteps, and Squint at By-ends, and ſtart aſide from God like a deceitful Bow: It is from hence that the Saints now and then faint in their Faith, cool in their Love, and halt and make ſtops in their Obedience: Watch therefore, O Chriſtian, againſt this cloſe evil, conſider the vileneſs of it, think with thy ſelf how greivous a thing it is to be falſe to that God, who makes all other things true to thee; the Sun to give thee true light, and the creatures true nouriſhment; the blood to run right in thy veines and the breath in thy noſtrils: loath and abhorr this abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing, cry to heaven for more truth in thy inward parts, labour to have the very power of Religion that thou maieſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60575:26"/>fill up thy profeſſion; mourn over thy Falls and withering Graces, check thy ſtarting heart and charg it to maintain a firm and cloſe adherence to God, ſet thy ſelf all manner of waies to root out and extirpate the remnants of hypocriſy out of thy heart, that, when thou comeſt to ſuffer for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, thy Heart may not decieve thee: Truth in the Heart is neceſſary in hearing, praying, repenting, believing, obeying but above all it is ſo in ſuffering for Chriſt; hypocriſy can perſonate all other graces, but uſually it ſtumbles and diſcovers itſelf in a day of trial; therefore mortify the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret guil that is in thy heart, that thou maieſt ſtand faſt under the croſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Mortify the vain ſuperſtition that is in the heart: It is natural to us to deſire the ſame thing as the children of Iſrael did, to have Gods to go before us, to have vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible images or pictures of the deity, a pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous and ſtately worſhip, a gaudy Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made up of humane additions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and ſuch a way of ſerving God as is accommodated to ſenſe and framed after the commandments of men; every one is ready to think in his falſe heart, what <hi>Ticonius</hi> ſaid with his lips,<note place="margin">Aug. Contr. Ep. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Quod volumus Sanctum eſt,</hi> that which we will is holy; That which in the worſhip of God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60575:27"/>is fine and decent, in our eyes, is ſo in Gods too: But conſider with thy ſelf; he that places his Religion in ſuch things as theſe, may chance to fall in Love with that fine <hi>Whore</hi> which is <hi>decked with gold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious stones, Revel.</hi> 17.4. He that will have a Religion ſutable to Senſe, will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtand to that Religion which hath a Croſs annexed to it: If the Command of man be the reaſon of thy Worſhip, thou wilt turn to every Point as that Command doth vary: If thou canſt nod in Superſtition, thou hadſt need watch leſt thou fall into flat Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. Remember, God is a Spirit; the true Worſhippers worſhip <hi>in Spirit and truth;</hi> and the true Worſhippers will prove the true ſufferers: Stand to the pure Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, thou maieſt not fall into a corrupt one: Worſhip God in Spirit, that thou maieſt never fall down to an Idol.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60575:27"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The third Direction for Suffering is the Knowledg of God. An ignorant man is not capable of ſuffering; neither will every knowledge ſerve the turn. The Knowledge, that prepares for Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, muſt be a well-rooted, a right eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating, a taſting or ſavouring, a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical or operative Knowledge.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe third Direction for ſuffering is this, if we would be in a fit poſture for ſuffering we muſt labour after the knowledge of God and the things of God: An ignotant man, who is a man in ſhape, but a beaſt in heart, is not a perſon capable of pious Suffering; He knows not the Principles of Religion, and for what ſhould he ſuffer? He hath no Principles of Grace in him, and how ſhould he ſuffer? He is in darkneſs, and to him Truth or Error, one God or more, pure Worſhip or Idolatry, are all one; he is <hi>alienated from the life of God, Eph.</hi> 4.18. and therefore it is not imaginable that he ſhould dye for God or his Truth: For him to ſuffer for an unknown God or Chriſt, is to ſuffer for he knows not what. As
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60575:28"/>the <hi>Samaritans</hi> worſhipped they knew not what; ſo the ignorant man, if he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, ſuffers for he knows not what. The <hi>Athenians</hi> had an Altar <hi>to the unknown God, Acts.</hi>
17.23. and poſſibly they offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up other Creatures to him: But for a man to offer up himſelf as a Sacrifice to an unknown God, and to part with all this World when he knows nothing of a better, is a very ſtrang unaccountable thing. Let us therefore cry after Wiſdom, and lift up our voice for Underſtanding: Let us <hi>ſeek her as ſilver, and ſearch for her as for hid Treaſures,</hi> as the Wiſeman exhorts <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.3. &amp; 4. Let our Prayers aſcend up to Heaven, to bring her down from thence; and our Endeavors dig in the Mines of Scripture to fetch her up from thence, that ſo
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> may <hi>keep</hi> us, as it is Verſe 11. Knowledge is a preſervative to him that hath it; <hi>the People that know their God ſhall be ſtrong, Dan.</hi> 11.32. <hi>The young men,</hi> who have <hi>the word. of God abiding</hi> in them, <hi>are strong</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.14.
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is a well-ſpring of life to him that hath it, Prov.</hi> 16.22. It ſtreams out in living Graces, and ſtrengthens the Inner-man, and prepares it for a day of trial; only it is to be remembred, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knowledge will not do this, but it muſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60575:28"/>be a well-rooted, a right eſtimating, a taſting or ſavouring, a practical or operative Knowledge that doth it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be a well-rooted Knowledge that will prepare us for ſuffering. <hi>Job</hi> tels his Friends, <hi>That the root of the matter,</hi> or, (as the original, will bear) <hi>the root of the wood was in him, Job</hi> 19.28. He was ſorely afflicted by God and men, yet he held faſt his integrity, becauſe he was not a man of meer Leaves, but had a root of Knowledge and Grace in him. It is with Chriſtians as it is with Trees, the more the Tree is rooted in the ground, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it ſtands in a ſtorm; the more a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is rooted in Evangelical Truths, the firmer he ſtands in a time of Perſecution. Thoſe of the <hi>ſtony ground received the word with joy,</hi> but fell off in time of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſecution <hi>becauſe they had no root in them ſelves,</hi> Math. 13.21. The Heavenly Truth did but lye upon the face of their Hearts, and never ſunk into them to become a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Principle in them. The Truth, that we would ſuffer for, had not need be a looſe Notion, but Truth in the hidden parts, faſtned there as a nail in a ſure place, ſealed up to the heart by the holy ſpirit, ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and innaturalized in the mind that we may not let it go: We had need be
<hi>groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſetled in the faith,</hi> as the Apoſtle
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60575:29"/>ſpeaks, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23. Grounded as an houſe upon a ſure Foundation, and ſetled as a man ſitting faſt in a Chair: We had need have a good Scripture bottom, and be firmly ſeated in the Truth, that we may be capable of ſuffering for Religion. The Scripture tels us, that <hi>there is but one God, one only to be worſhipped and ſerved,</hi> that <hi>his glory may not be given to another,</hi> nor <hi>his praiſe to graven Images;</hi> that <hi>Idols are ſilver and gold, the work of mens hands;</hi> that <hi>they have mouths and ſpeak not, eyes and ſee not, ears and hear not, noſes and ſmell not, hands and handle not, feet and walk not,</hi> that the Makers and Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of them are like unto them, as ſtupid as the ſenſeleſs Images are; that an Idol is nothing, a thing of no moment or power at all, a meer nothing to be it ſelf made a God, or ſo much as to repreſent one. If ſuch truths as theſe (of which St.
<hi>Cyprian</hi> hath given a great Catalogue in his Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Martyrdome) be intimately radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the heart, they will ſtrengthen it againſt Idolatry.<note place="margin">Magd. Hiſt. Cent. 4. cap. 12.</note> The glorious Martyr <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lalia</hi> ſeemed to be full of them, when in her great ſufferings ſhe ſung, that <hi>Iſis, Apollo, Venus,</hi> were nothing, and <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imianus</hi> the worſhipper of them was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf nothing: O let us adhere to the holy
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60575:29"/>Truths in the Word; theſe came down from Heaven, and like their Original are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but pure Truth without any mixture of Error in them; theſe appear to us in the light of the firſt Truth, and lead to the bliſs-making Viſion of him in Heaven; and as we deſire to be there, let us firmly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to them, eſpecially to the word of Chriſts Patience; The Truth that muſt be ſuffered for at ſuch at time as this, to that we muſt cleave cloſeſt, becauſe in that will be the greateſt ſtreſs and trial. It is good to be eſtabliſhed in all Truth, but now it is in a ſpecial manner neceſſary to be well fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Truth that concerns the Pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which runs very low in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, while in the mean while the Idolatrous one is like to be triumphant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be a right eſtimating Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that will prepare us for ſuffering, Every Notion of the things of God will not do it; he, that hath an high notion of them, but a low eſtimation, hath but a knowledge falſly ſo called; he knows them not as he ought to know them, becauſe he knows them only to know them, but not to value them: We muſt ſo know them, as to rate them above a World; this is of great moment in order to Suffering: A man is capable to ſuffer, or not, according as his eſtimate of Spiritual things is higher
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60575:30"/>or lower. When the Martyr <hi>Polycarp</hi> was urged by the Proconſul to deny Chriſt,<note place="margin">Euſtb, Lio.
<hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> his anſwer was, <hi>A potioribus non eſſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeundum ad pejora;</hi> we muſt not paſs from better things to worſe. He eſteemed Chriſt better then the World, and therefore he ſuffered for him: But if he had eſteemed the World better then Chriſt, he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been a Martyr: As the eſtimation is ſo is the man. We know the Evangelical Truth, but if we do not rate it higher then all the World, we ſhall never be able to ſuffer for it: It is indeed in itſelf a glorious Beam let down from Heaven, a pure diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the great Salvation that is in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and in that reſpect incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly more worth then all the World; but if we do not ſo account it, we ſhall fall from it to embrace the World as being better in our eyes. It is very remarkable, that when the Emperors Preſect allured the great <hi>Baſil</hi> to the <hi>Arrian</hi> Doctrine,<note place="margin">Tneod. b. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a ſmall thing, the holy man an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>That he would not part with one ſyllable of Scripture, no, not to ſave his life.</hi> Such an eſteem of Truth is of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe to make a man adhere to it in an evil day. We know the pure worſhip, but if we do not prize it above all earthly things, we ſhall never be able to ſuffer for it: It is in itſelf a thing exceeding preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60575:30"/>it is the choiceſt part of life that is ſpent in it; the honor of God is more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately concerned in it then in other things. That noble Convert <hi>Galeacius Caracciolus,</hi> who left all for Chriſt, prized one days Communion with Chriſt more than all the Gold or Silver in the World: And if we can rate it ſo, we ſhall never turn aſide from it to the Idolatrous World, nor be carried into ſin by the ſtream of the Time: Or ſay as one going to <hi>Maſs</hi> did, <hi>Eamus ad communem errorem;</hi> let us go to the Common Error. We know the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt is to be promoted, but if we do not value it above our own Reputation, we ſhall never ſuffer reproach for him. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> eſteemed the reproach of Chriſt greater riches then the treaſures of <hi>Egypt, Hebx.</hi> 11.26. Reproach in itſelf is a vile thing, no way eſtimable, but the reproach of Chriſt hath an honor in it, and outſhines all the glories of the World.
<hi>Marſacus,</hi> a French Souldier, being adjudged with others to the Fire, and for his Military ſervice not having, as others had,<note place="margin">Thuan Lib. <hi>12.</hi> An. <hi>1553.</hi>
               </note> a With put about his neck, demands the reaſon why he might not be permitted to wear ſuch a Chain as his Fellows did, and to be made of the ſame illuſtrious order as they were of. If we have ſuch a Divine Spirit, as this is, in us,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60575:31"/>we ſhall count in an high honor to ſuffer reproach for Chriſt. A right eſtimation of things, is an excellent help to bear ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings for Religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It muſt be a taſting or Savouring Knowledge that will prepare us for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">Treat. of Faith. cap. 9.</note>
               <hi>It is the taſte of God's Word</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>lackſon</hi>)
<hi>that ſweetens ſufferings to us, and makes us couragious to adventure up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all difficulties that are objected to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as from entring into the land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe;</hi> Such ſpeculative conceits of the Food of Life as we may find in the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, are of as little force to inflame our hearts with longing after that Heavenly Kingdom, as Poetical Deſcriptions of far Countries, are to make us undertake their Conqueſt: We muſt have Knowledge and Senſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9. Theory and Experience too, to make us ſtand in the evil day; we muſt <hi>taſt and ſee</hi> that <hi>the Lord is gracious,</hi> that we may be able to ſuffer for him. A ſpiritual reliſh of the ſweet ſtreams of Grace that flow from him, is a choice prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to make us take and drink of the bitter Cup. <hi>Gotteſchalcus</hi> ſuffered a cloſe impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment for twenty years together, meerly for preaching up the Doctrine of Grace; and it is without queſtion, that he had not a meer Notion, but an experimental
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60575:31"/>taſte of it in his Suffering: Many have the Knowledge of Chriſt in a way of Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but we muſt have the Savour of his Sweet Ointments upon our heart that we may follow him into Suffering. We had need feel the ſweetneſs of his blood in the calms of Conſcience, that we may Shed our own blood for him: Let us not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves to have Chriſt only in our Bibles, but endeavor to have a proof of him in our Hearts; a proof of his ſweet-ſmelling Sacrifice in our inward peace; a proof of his rich Anointings in our ſupplies of Grace: The experience of Chriſt in us, is a ſtrong encouragement to ſuffer for him. He that hath a Chriſt only in Notion, will fall off from him, but he that hath a tried Chriſt will hardly leave him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It muſt be a Knowledge practical and operative in the life, that will prepare us for ſuffering: A meer notional Knowledge of Chriſt is not a right one: He that ſaith, <hi>I know him, and keepeth not his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him,</hi> 1.
<hi>Joh.</hi> 2.4. Such an one contradicts himſelf; his Converſation gives the lie to his Profeſſion; the Truth is not in him in a practical way; his Knowledge is but a Flaſh, a vaniſhing Vapor, that gives no vital influence to his life; he will not do
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60575:32"/>other Commands, much leſs will he <hi>take up the Croſs,</hi> which is a Command more grievous to Senſe then others are. He, that would be prepared for Sufferings, muſt labor for ſuch a knowledge as gives a proof of itſelf in holy Obedience: Doing is a good preparative for ſuffering; he that ſincerely doth other Commands, will <hi>take up</hi> his
<hi>Croſs</hi> too, that being a Command as well as others: He, that indeed is ſubject to Gods commanding Will, will be ſubject to his diſpoſing one too, which orders the coming of the croſs to us: It is the active Chriſtian that will, if occaſion ſerve, be paſſive. Our Saviour Chriſt doth notably ſet forth what kind of Chriſtians will ſtand in time of Perſecution, and what will fall: He that heareth his <hi>ſayings and doth them, builds upon the rock,</hi> and <hi>when the ſtorm comes,</hi> he <hi>ſtands faſt, becauſe he is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Rock, Math.</hi>
7.24.25. that is, he is founded upon Chriſt by Faith and Ocedience; and in the Storm he continues upon him by Patience; the Rock bears him up as a part of itſelf: But he that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſts <hi>ſayings, and doth them not, builds upon the ſand, and when the ſtorm comes,</hi> he fals. Verſ. 26,
27. Becauſe he is upon the Sand; he hath no true Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his Religion, he never did dig
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60575:32"/>deep enough to come to Self-denial, and therefore in the Storm, his fall is very great, he and his Religion utterly periſh; as when a houſe is broke up from the very Foundation, or a Tree is blown up by the Roots. Therefore if we would ſtand firm and unmovable in a Storm, let us labor to have Such a lively and operative Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, as may diffuſe itſelf into an univerſal Obedience to his precepts: He, that enures himſelf to do the Will of God, will be ready, when the Croſs comes, to take it up, and ſay, <hi>This is the Will of God too and muſt be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, that we may have this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Knowledge, we muſt not only read the holy Scriptures, but with <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> look up to Heaven for that holy Spirit that is able to lead us into all Truth, and to ſeal it upon our hearts for ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:60575:33"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The fourth direction for Suffering is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Faith; This hath a triple reſpect; areſpect to God, his providence, Power, and Grace: Areſpect to Christ, as a propitiation, a Pattern. an Head and Helper: Areſpect to the Promiſes; the Promiſes of Gods Preſence, the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Confirmation, the Promiſes of a good Iſſue.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe fourth Direction is this, if we would be in a fit poſture for Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt labour after a pretious Faith: A Dogmatical Faith will not do it; the Devil himſelf, who is the Chief Agent in Perſecution, hath ſuch a Faith; neither will a temporary Faith do it, this is but a meer bloſſom, that fals off in a ſtorm of Perſecution; it muſt be a pretious Faith, a Furnace Faith, that will endure the fiery Trial: This is the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Shield</hi> like a door, broad enough to cover the Soul and all its Graces, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.16. this is to be taken above all other pieces of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Armor; it is eminent among the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as the Sun is among the Planets: It is the great conquering Grace; all other Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60575:33"/>act in conjunction with it. In the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſtiled by ſome the little Book of
<hi>Martyrs,</hi> the Saints are brought in doing and ſuffering great things, but all is aſcribed to Faith, as the Captain-grace of all the reſt, the firſt mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to other Graces: It works by Love, and not only ſo but by Meekneſs, Obedience, Patience, running like blood and Spirits in every part of the New-creature. Faith hath a triple reſpect, to God, to Chriſt, to the Promiſes, and in each of theſe it is of ſingular uſe in order to ſufferings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith hath a reſpect to God; it makes its approaches to him, nay, it fixes the the Soul in him as in its Center. Hence it is that the
<hi>righteous fears no evil tidings, becauſe his Heart is fixed, truſting in the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 112.7. The word rowles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, but he by faith ſtands faſt in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable God. Hence it is that the Church becomes unmoveable too. <hi>God is in the midſt of her, ſhe ſhall not be moved, Pſal.</hi> 46.5. There are three things in God which Faith fixes upon in order to pious Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith fixes upon his Providence. The Stoick could ſay,
<hi>That there was no living in a World empty of God and Providence:</hi> Much more may the Chriſtian that is toſſed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60575:34"/>up and down in a perſecuting World, ſay ſo. But his Faith tels him, that perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion comes not by Chance, Man rages, but God reigns: The World is as a tempeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous Sea, but God ſits at the Sterne and governs all: He limits the fury of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors; the wrath of man ſhall praiſe him; <hi>the remainder of wrath,</hi> (or as it is in the original)
<hi>the remainder of wraths he will reſtrain Pſalm.</hi> 76.10. He lets out wrath in the ſingular number, and reſtrains wraths in the plural; nothing of it comes forth but what is permitted; nothing of it is permitted but the minor part only. He it is that orders the ſufferings of the Saints: Senſe indeed ſees only the outward Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but Faith knows, that there is a live, a Divine Order in it: Senſe looks at the wicked hands that are red with the blood of Innocents, but Faith looks at the holy hand that is in it: This is one thing, that bears up good men, that their Father in Heaven diſpoſes of all.<note place="margin">Spond. An. 451.</note> When <hi>Attila</hi> called himſelf, <hi>Flagellum Dei,</hi> the ſcurge of God; <hi>Lupus</hi> bid him come and do as he pleaſed. When Chriſtians by Faith look on Perſecutors as the rod and ſtaff in Gods hand, they are ready to Subject themſelves to the Croſs: <hi>It is better, if the will of God be ſo, that ye ſuffer for well-doing,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60575:34"/>than for evil-doing,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. That in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed phraſe <hi>(if the will of God be ſo)</hi> is very remarkable to Believers: were there nothing in their Sufferings but the Will of bloody men, they would bear them more hardly and unwillingly; but becauſe the Will of the good God is there, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure them more eaſily and freely then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they would do: They know very well that God will turn all to good; his ends are far other then thoſe of Satan and his Inſtruments. Our Saviour tels the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> that <hi>the Devil ſhould caſt ſome of them into Priſon, that they might be tried, Rev.</hi> 2.10. In which words it is to be obſerved, that Gods end is joined unto Satans act: Satan would have them in Chains, but God would try them that their Graces might come forth as gold out of the fire. The <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Monarch meant <hi>to cutt off Nations</hi> not a few, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 10.7. but God meant to
<hi>chaſtiſe his People,</hi> and then <hi>to burn the Rod,</hi> Verſ.
12, &amp; 17. He, that by Faith can ſee the holy Land and ends of God in Perſecution, will be ready to ſuffer under it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Faith fixes upon his Power. When <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> were threatned with a fiery Furnace for not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Golden Image, their anſwer
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60575:35"/>was, <hi>Our God is able to deliver</hi> us,
<hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17. Perſecutors may be ſtrong, but Faith aſſures the Soul that God is much ſtronger, and can deliver his People; nay, and will do it alſo; not, as thoſe three Worthies were, in a viſible manner, yet in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible one: Suffering Saints, have ever found by experience that the Power of God hath bore them up in their Sufferings. When <hi>Coelocerius,</hi> in the Perſecution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Emperor <hi>Adrian,</hi> ſaw the ſupports and patience that <hi>Fauſtina</hi> &amp; <hi>Jobita</hi> had in their ſufferings for Chriſt, he cried out, <hi>Vere magnus Deus Chriſtianorum;</hi> the God of the Chriſtians is truly great. When
<hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſaw the Martyrs cheerfully dying for their Religion, he thereupon fell off from <hi>Plato's</hi> School to Chriſt: St.
<hi>Paul</hi> the great experienced Sufferer, exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to be partaker of the Afflictions of the Goſpel, <hi>according to the power of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8. that is he ſhould ſuffer not in his own power, but in God's. Think thus with thy ſelf, O Chriſtian, God can and will give ſuch internal Supports and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts as ſhall more then counterpoiſe all thy Sufferings for him: Fix thy Faith upon his Power, and thou canſt not fail in the Trial.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faith fixes upon his Grace and mercy:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60575:35"/>Men are cruel, but God is gracious and merciful to his People at all times, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in a time of Trial: He chuſes them <hi>in the Furnace of Affliction, Eſay.</hi> 48.10. When men reprobate them as the off-ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things, then God doth as it were chuſe them afreſh; I mean, his electing love, which was in his heart towards them, as early as eternity it ſelf, doth then break out in freſh acts of Grace towards them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that it was free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>given</hi> to them <hi>in the behalf of Chriſt not only to believe on him, but to ſuffer for his ſake, Phil.</hi> 1.29. Faith which is the firſt guift, and Suffering which is the laſt in this life, do both iſſue out from the Fountain of Grace. Caſt thy ſelf, O Chriſtian, upon the Grace and Mercy of thy good God; that Grace, which cals, juſtifies, ſanctifies thee, will alſo give thee the guift of ſuffering; that mercy, which ſpares thee in thy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary duties, will in a time of Suffering be indulgent over thee in a more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner: The mercy of God will be upon us according as we truſt in him; the ſweeteſt Strains of Mercy are reſerved for the higheſt acts of Faith, which are ſeen more in Sufferings then in other things. If we carry Faith with us into Priſons and fiery Furnaces, Goodneſs and Mercy will
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60575:36"/>follow us thither in an eminent way. Faith hath a reſpect to Chriſt, it comes to him as to a Center of reſt, receives him as a pretious guift, leans on him as a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; nay,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it individuates and appropriates him to the Soul. There are three things in Chriſt which Faith looks to in order to Suffering.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith looks to him as a Propitiation: It hides in his Wounds, as in the clefts of the Rock; it waſhes the ſoul in that
<hi>atoning blood that cleanſes from all ſin,</hi> Hereby the Chriſtian is ſo ſtrengthned in the Inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that he can <hi>glory in Tribulations, Rom.</hi> 5.3. The World perſecutes, but he hath peace with God; man hates, but he hath the Love of God in his Heart; Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings may come, but they fall only upon the outward man; there is no ſting within, nor guilt preſſing upon Conſcience. When <hi>Luther</hi> was in fear of an Apoplexy, he cried out, <hi>Feri, Domine, feri, paratus ſum, quia à peccatis abſolutus;</hi> ſtrike, Lord, ſtrike, I am ready, becauſe abſolved from Sin. A Chriſtian, that is waſhed from ſin in the blood of Jeſus, may bear the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting ſtroke; he hath <hi>refrigerium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> a ſweet refreſhment from Chriſt's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement in that inward peace, which is made by it in Conſcience.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60575:36"/>
            <p n="2">2. Faith looks to Chriſt as a Pattern: He is not only a Propitiation to be truſted in, but a Pattern to be imitated by us: He
<hi>ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſteps,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. Whom ſhould we follow but our Lord and Saviour? How can we Spare our own blood, if we be waſhed in his? He drunk up the bitter Cup to the bottom, and ſhall we not take ſome drops of it? He bore the wrath of God for us, and ſhall we not bear the wrath of man for him? He learned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience by the things which he ſuffered, and how much more ſhould we poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do ſo? He entred by ſuffering into glory; and why ſhould we dream of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way thither? If we would be ready to ſuffer, let us <hi>look unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, deſpiſing the ſhame;</hi> Let us <hi>conſider him that endured ſuch contradiction of ſinners againſt himſelf, leſt we be weary and faint in our minds, Hebr.</hi> 12.2, 3. The noble <hi>Alzearius,</hi> being asked,<note place="margin">Arr. Tact. 161.</note> how he could ſo patiently bear injuries, anſwered thus; <hi>Converto me ad injurias Chriſti,</hi> I turn me to the injuries done to my Saviour. We muſt look to Chriſt's Croſs, that we may bear our own it being now, no longer
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60575:37"/>meer ſuffering, but ſanctified by the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our Saviour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faith looks to Chriſt as an Head and Helper: He is not a meer Pattern, but an Head and Helper too; Were there no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſupporting Grace for the Saints but that little in their own boſome, they might expect to fail in the Trial; but there is an inexhauſtible Fountain of Grace in their Head in Heaven, and that will bear them up in all their Sufferings. This made St. <hi>Paul</hi> glory in Perſecutions, becauſe the <hi>Power of Chriſt</hi> would <hi>reſt upon</hi> him; and when he was <hi>weak</hi> in himſelf, he was <hi>ſtrong</hi> in that, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9, 10. St.
<hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt in the Martyrs, ſaith, <hi>Qui pro nobis mortem ſemel vicit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 9. ad Mort.</note>
               <hi>ſemper vincit in nobis;</hi> he that once overcame death for us, alwais overcomes it in us: This the Martyr <hi>Blandina,</hi> though weak in body, found by experience, being bore up in the midſt of Torments by the Power of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Euſeb. L. 5. cap. 1.</note> and finding a freſh refreſhment; as often as ſhe ſaid, <hi>Chriſtiana ſum,</hi> I am a Chriſtian. The ſame was ſeen in the Martyr <hi>Sanctus,</hi> who bore various Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments above all humane Strength, becauſe he was bedewed and confirmed out of the Celeſtial <hi>Fountain of living water</hi> flowing down from Chriſt. Whatever thou doeſt, O
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60575:37"/>Chriſtian, be ſure to apply thy ſelf by Faith unto the neverfailing Fountain of Grace in him, that thou mayſt have ſuch Supplies of Grace, as may bear thee up in an evil day.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faith hath a reſpect to the Promiſes; Theſe are the Breaſts of Conſolation, the Channels in which the Grace in Gods heart flows down to the Sons of men: Here the Chriſtian may provide himſelf with Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als againſt the time of ſuffering. I ſhall here only mention three kinds of Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for Faith to live upon in a day of Trial.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith muſt live upon the Promiſes of Gods gratious Preſence: God tels his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that he <hi>will be with</hi> them <hi>in the fire and in the water, Eſay.</hi> 43.2. that is, in all danger and calamities whatſoever; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall this Preſence be for a little time only, but conſtant and perpetual: He <hi>will never leave them, nor forſake them, Hebr.</hi> 13.5. This is a choice comfort to good men, that in Tribulations they are not left alone, but God is with them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> had experience of this; all men <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> ſtood <hi>with him and ſtrengthned him,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16, 17. The Preſence of God was to him more then a World, and able to ſupport him againſt all his Adverſaries. St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ſpeaking of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60575:38"/>the Martyrs in his time,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 9.</note> ſaith, That God was not a meer ſpectator in their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but <hi>ipſe luctatur in nobis, ipſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congreditur, ipſe in certamine coronat, pariter &amp; coronatur;</hi> he ſtrives in us, he encounters our adverſaries, he crowns us in the Battel, and is himſelf crowned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Let us therefore by Faith reſt upon the promiſe of Gods Preſence, and aſſure our hearts that he will be with us in our Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>All the Promiſes of God are Yea and Amen in Chriſt,</hi> and his being <hi>Immanuel, God with us</hi> in the humane Nature, is a Pledge to the Saints, that God will be with them in their Sufferings for him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Faith muſt live up on the promiſes of Confirmation. The Apoſtle tels the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> That <hi>God ſhall confirm them unto the end;</hi> and adds this as a reaſon, <hi>God is faithful by whom ye are called into the fellowſhip of his ſon Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi>
1, <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.89. God doth as it were pawn his faithfulneſs upon it, that they being once brought into union with Chriſt, ſhall never fall off, but be confirmed unto the end: <hi>The gates of hell ſhall never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt them; they ſhall be kept through faith unto ſalvation;</hi> nay, and their Faith ſhall be kept too. Chriſt did not only pray for
<hi>Peter,</hi> that his <hi>Faith fail not,</hi> but he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60575:38"/>prays ſo for all the faithful: Oh how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable are ſuch promiſes to the Saints! Let us by faith lay up theſe rich Cordials in our hearts to keep up from fainting in Perſecution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faith muſt live upon the Promiſes of a good Iſſue:
<hi>All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth to his people, Pſal.</hi>
23.10. <hi>All things ſhall work together for their good, Rom.</hi> 8.28. Perſecutions and all. God alters the property of his Peoples Afflictions, and by an Almighty Alchimy turns Droſs into Gold; he makes perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion turn to the refining of the Saints Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to the glorifying of his own great name: O! what great good things doth he bring out of evil? How much of his Love and faithfulneſs may be ſeen in the Croſs? Let us therefore fix our hearts upon ſuch promiſes, that, paſſing through the fiery Trial, we may ſee the good end the Lord makes of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:60575:39"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The fift Direction for Suffering, is Love to God and Chriſt. Love to God; ſuch as value him deſire him, delight in him, and will and endeavour to ſerve and honour him: Love to Chriſt, ſuch as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue him, deſire him, delight in him, and will and endeavour to ſerve and honour him.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe fiſt Direction is this; if we would be in a fit poſture for ſuffering, we muſt get a ſincere Love to God and Chriſt; St.<note place="margin">De Civit. Lib. 14. cap. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>That two Loves made two Cities; the Love of ſelf made the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly City, the Love of God makes the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one; the perſecutor dwels in the one, and the Martyr in the other.</hi> There is an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimilating efficacy in Love whereby it caſts the mind into the Mould of the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved;<note place="margin">Siterram amas terra es; ſi Deum, quidni di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerem Deus es.
<hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> If thou love Earth, thou art Earth; if thou Love God, thou art partaker of the Divine Nature, and doſt reſemble God himſelf. The greateſt impediment to pious ſuffering is the Love of the World and ſelf; and the greateſt preparative to it is the Love of God and Chriſt. I ſhall firſt ſpeak of love to God, as a preparative thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60575:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>and then of Love to Chriſt as ſuch.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love to God is a preparative to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering: If we love him above all things, no outward Object will draw us from him; if we love him with all the heart, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Luſt will make us fall from him. Love to him ſtands in four things; each of which will diſpoſe us to ſuffer for him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love to him ſtands in an high valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him; it eſteems him to be ſuch an one as he is ſet forth in Scripture: To be
<hi>the only wiſe God,</hi> the <hi>only Potentate,</hi> the <hi>only One that is good;</hi> to be all theſe eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, fontally, ſupereminently: He, that hath ſuch an eſtimate of him, will be ready to ſuffer for him: To ſuch an one it is folly to learn the <hi>only Wiſe,</hi> weakneſs to leave the <hi>only</hi> Potentate, miſery to leave the <hi>only Good;</hi> And how can he leave ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent an Object? to ſuch an one it is pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to adhere to the <hi>only Wiſe,</hi> ſtrength to adhere to the <hi>only Potentate,</hi> happineſs to adhere to the <hi>only Good;</hi> And how can he chuſe but adhere to him? It was the ſaying of an Ancient,<note place="margin">Minut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Tum dignè Deum aeſtimamus cum inaeſtimabilem dicimus;</hi> then we rightly eſteem God, when we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him ineſtimable. Eſtates, Bodies, Lives may be valued, but he is infinitely beyond all eſtimation: All creatures are
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60575:40"/>but as ſhadows, and little drops of being in compariſon of him; It is a juſt debt we owe to him, to rate him incomparably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, and in ſo doing the Soul it ſelf is ennobled and made fit to ſuffer for him: As a man by valuing the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove itſelf, becomes baſe and brutiſh, and <hi>like the Beaſts that periſh;</hi> ſo a man by eſtimating God above all things, becomes heroical and Divine, <hi>and like the Angels</hi> that live altogether upon him: Such an one is able to part with life in the Channel, to have it in the Fountain; to let go all other things, to have all in the one All-ſufficient God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love to God ſtands in holy D ſires after him; it makes the ſoul <hi>pant after him; as the heart panteth after the Waterbrooks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duleiſſimo Deo totus immergi cupit &amp; inviſcerari. Carthus.</note> and go out of itſelf in holy anhelations af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter union with him: Such is the Heavenly property of it, that it aſpires to be one Spirit with him, to have <hi>idem Velle</hi> and <hi>idem Nolle,</hi> to will as he wills, and nill as he nills; and when once our Wills are melted into his; every thing that comes from him will be welcome to us. Though Fleſh and Blood may cry out of Suffering, as a very hard thing, yet Love will ſay, that nothing can be wiſer or better then that which our Father orders and laies out
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60575:40"/>for us. If deſire after God as the ſupream good once put our Souls into motion, we ſhall follow him not into Ordinances only, but into Sufferings alſo: His gratious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is in both; In Ordinances it is in a good meaſure, but in Sufferings, which are the higheſt Services on Earth, it is in a more eminent manner. God doth not barely ſay to his afflicted people, <hi>I am with thee;</hi> but <hi>I will ſtrengthen thee;</hi> yea, <hi>I will help thee; yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my Righteouſneſs; Eſay.</hi> 41.10. many words are heaped up together to impart the excellency of his preſence with them. O let our hearts burn within us with ardent deſires after him, that we may be able to bear the fiery Trial at its coming.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love to God ſtands in an holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence in him; it makes the Soul reſt upon him as <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove did upon the Ark, and Center in him as in the ſupream Good. Holy deſires end in inward ſatisfaction; <hi>David</hi> thirſting after God comes to have his
<hi>ſoul ſatisfied</hi> as with <hi>marrow and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Pſal.</hi>
63.5. And Chriſtians that breathe after him, come to have ſweet ſpiritual joys and delights, taſts of Heaven and drops from the pure rivers of pleaſures that are above: Theſe are able to ſweeten
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60575:41"/>the bittereſt ſufferings. It is ſaid of the
<hi>Theſſalonians, that they received the word in much affliction with joy of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 1.6. The Goſpel doth not go alone, but Affliction accompanies it; neither will affliction go down alone, but the joy of the holy Ghoſt ſweetens it: The bleſſed Martyrs have experimentally found theſe divine joys in their hearts. It is ſaid of
<hi>Alexander</hi> the Martyr,<note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. Cent. 2. Chapt.
12.</note> famous for his Love to God, that <hi>ne ingemuit,</hi> he did not ſo much as fetch a groan in the midſt of his Torments; and doubtleſs he had ſtrong conſolations within to bear him up in his Sufferings. The Martyr
<hi>Algerius</hi> being in priſon wrote thus; <hi>in the dark Dungeon I find a Paradiſe of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; in a place of ſorrow dwells tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; in an Infernal Cave I have joy of Soul: O how good is the Lord! How eaſy and ſweet his yoke! Such</hi> Heavenly Cordials will bare up Chriſtians in the greateſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als: O let us labour to delight our ſouls in God, that we may be able to ſuffer for him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Love to God ſtands in an holy Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence towards him; it delivers and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renders up the whole man to him; it wills and endeavors (ſo far as a poor Creature can to an Infinite Creator) to bring all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60575:41"/>and glory to him. Thus <hi>the</hi> 24.
<hi>elders fel down before him and caſt down their crowns,</hi> ſaying
<hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive glory, and honour, and power, Revel.</hi> 4.10, 11. renouncing themſelves they referr all that they have and are to him alone: This is an excellent prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to Suffering. If we would indeed ſerve him, we muſt be willing to ſuffer for him; for that is the higheſt Service that can be done to him on earth: If we would indeed glorify him, we muſt be ready to Suffer for him; for that is the greateſt glory that we can poſſibly give unto him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we do practically declare to all the World, that God is our All, Riches, Honours, Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Life it ſelf, are as nothing to him. O let us labor to ſurrender up our ſelves to him in other things, that we may not fail to make the greateſt ſurrender of all in Suffering.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love to Chriſt is a preparative to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering:
<hi>Ignatius</hi> (whoſe Motto was, <hi>Amor meus crucifixus,</hi> My Love was crucified) would ſuffer any thing for Chriſt. The Martyr
<hi>Felicitas</hi> was ſo in love with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. Cent. 2. cap. 12.</note> that ſhe would not only ſuffer herſelf, but have her ſeven ſons ſuffer for him alſo. Love to Chriſt ſtands in four things, each of which will diſpoſe us to ſuffer for him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love to Chriſt ſtands in an high Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luation
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60575:42"/>of him; it eſteems him altogether pretious: Pretious in his Perſon, being <hi>Immanuel,</hi> God and man in one; pretious in his atoning ſufferings, which (being by his Deity elevated into a kind of infinity) were enough to pay for the ſin of a World; pretious in his holy words; his Myſteries being heights, his Commands rectitude, his Promiſes Grace: pretious in the rich Treaſures of Grace, which are in him, and everflowing out towards Believers: He that thus eſteems of him will be ready to ſuffer for him. To leave his atoning ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings is to run into Hell; to leave his words is to run into all Error; to leave his Treaſures of Grace is to run into Spiritual Poverty: And how can we leave him? To adhere to his Atonement is peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; to adhere to his Words is to keep the way of life; to adhere to his Treaſures of Grace, is to have continual influences of grace from him: And how can we chuſe but adhere to him? St. <hi>Paul</hi> counted all things <hi>droſs</hi> and <hi>dung</hi> for him, <hi>Phil.</hi>
3.8. St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in his Exhortation to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, gives this as one rule, that we ſhould <hi>nihil Chriſto praeponere,</hi> prefer nothing before Chriſt. To eſteem any thing better then him, is the way to turn Apoſtate; but to eſteem him better then
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60575:42"/>all, is the way to ſtand in a day of Trial.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love to Chriſt ſtands in holy deſires after him; it cauſes a man to long and faint for him, and, as one in extremity, to cry out,
<hi>Give me Chriſt, or elſe I dye:</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the laver of his blood, I dye in my ſins; without the ſupplies of his Grace, I dye in my wants: O! that I may have him! the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> was <hi>ſick of Love,</hi> languiſhing and ready to fall into a Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Swoon with her paſſionate deſires after him and his gratious Preſence; nothing in all the World could cure or ſatisfie her, but his all-deſirable ſelf. That ſoul that truly deſireth Chriſt, doth not deſire <hi>aliud praeter illum, aliud tanquam illum, aliud poſt illum;</hi> any thing beſides him, any thing equally to him, any thing after him: Such an ardor and holy flame of Love, as this is, is an extatical thing; it makes a man go out of himſelf to ſeek after him; it will <hi>ſell all</hi> for him, and, like thoſe virgin ſouls, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.4. <hi>follow him whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth;</hi> not only into the Banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-houſe of Ordinances, but into Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Afflictions for him. The Martyr <hi>Gordius</hi> had ſuch an ardent Love to Chriſt.<note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. Cent. 4. cap. 12.</note> that he was ready to ſuffer, <hi>mille mortes,</hi> a thouſand deaths for the name of Jeſus Chriſt, O let us Labour to have our hearts
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60575:43"/>kindled and inflamed with holy deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, that we may be able to ſtand and endure the fiery trial.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love to Chriſt ſtands in an holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence in him, it makes the ſoul enjoy a kind of heaven in his Preſence, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light itſelf in his ſatisfying Sweetneſs. The Spouſe in the
<hi>Canticles</hi> was <hi>raviſhed,</hi> and, as it were, ſwallowed up in him; the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his ſweet Ointments lay upon her heart; his Love was better to her then all the Wine of the World; ſhe ſat under the broad ſhadow of his Merits with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, Pardons and Graces dropping down from the Tree of Life upon her; he is in her eyes, <hi>totus deſideria,</hi> all loves or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; every thing in him hath a divine ſweetneſs in it. This ſpiritual joy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in Chriſt our Saviour, is an excellent preparative in order to ſuffering: The Church will have him lie all night
<hi>between her breaſts Cant.</hi> 1.13. all night, that is, in times of fear and temptation, that his preſence may ſweeten the bittereſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to her. The Croſs of Jeſus, if we taſt the ſweetneſs of it, will turn a Marah into joy and comfort: <hi>Tua praeſentia, Domine, Laurentio ipſam craticulam dulcem fecit;</hi> thy preſence, O Lord, made the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gridiron ſweet to St. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60575:43"/>an Ancient. <hi>Philip Lantgrave</hi> of
<hi>Heſſe,</hi> being a long time Priſoner under <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, felt the divine conſolations of Martyrs ſupporting of him. O let us labor to taſt more of the ſweetneſs of Chriſt, to find his blood in every Pardon, his Spirit in every Grace, his Wine-cellar in every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, that the Divine Comforts, that we experimentally feel in him, may ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Croſs to us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Love to Chriſt ſtands in an holy Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence towards him; it ſurrenders up the whole man to him; it endeavours to ſerve and honour him to the utmoſt. Thus thoſe many thouſands cry out, <hi>worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain to receive power, and riches, and wiſdom, and ſtrength, and honour, and glory, and bleſſing. Rev.</hi> 5.11, 12. they give all to Chriſt. This is an excellent Preparative for Suffering: If we would ſerve him in other things, we muſt ſerve him in ſuffering for him; if we would honour him in obedience to other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, we muſt honour him in taking up the Croſs too. St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſired, that
<hi>Chriſt might be magnified</hi> in his body, <hi>whether it were by life or by death: Phil.</hi> 1.20. If he lived he would magnifie Chriſt by Active Obedience; and if he died, he would do it by Paſſive: Either way he would
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60575:44"/>have Chriſt glorified in him.<note place="margin">Tot lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant-ora, quot ſunt vulnera. <hi>Magd. hiſt. Cent. 4. cap. 12.</hi>
               </note> The Martyr <hi>Romanus,</hi> having a multitude of wounds in his body, thanked the Perſecutor for opening ſo many mouths to glorify Chriſt. In nothing is Chriſt ſo much glorified as, in his ſuffering Saints; therein they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the higheſt Love, Seal up the Evangelical Truths with their own blood; practically prefer Chriſt before all the World, and offer up themſelves for him who gave himſelf a Sacrifice for them. O let us labor to make a total reſignation of our ſelves to him, that if ſufferings come, we may be able to bear them for his ſake.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The ſixth Direction for ſuffering, is a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope of eternal Life: Hope aſſures us, that there is another World, that the good things of it exceed thoſe of this, that we have an intereſt in them: Hope diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes us for them; Hope waits for them unto the end.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe ſixth Direction is this: If we would be in a fit poſture for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt get a lively hope of eternal Life: As our life is a Sea, Hope is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60575:44"/>to an Anchor, which makes us ſtand ſteady in a ſtorm: As our life is a warfare, Hope is compared to an Helmet, which covers the ſoul in times of danger: As the body liveth <hi>Spirando,</hi> by breathing, ſo the Soul lives <hi>Sperando,</hi> by hoping. A man cannot drown ſo long as his head is above water; Hope lifts up the head, and looks up to the Redemption and Salvation that is to come in another World in its ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and perfection. Hope doth three things; it aſſures good things to come; it diſpoſes us for them; it waits for them unto the end: Each of which will be of ſingular uſe to fit us for pious Sufferings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hope aſſures good things to come: It is called <hi>the Hope of Salvation, Theſſal.</hi> 5.8. <hi>the hope of Glory, Rom.</hi> 5.2.
<hi>the hope of eternal</hi> Life, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. becauſe it aſſures theſe things: To this I ſhall ſpeak in three Particulars</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hope aſſures us that there is another World, called in Scripture <hi>the World to come;</hi> without this there can be no foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for pious Suffering; no man can free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part with this World unleſs he be aſſured of another: <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. Miſerable indeed, to be perſecuted out of one World, and to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60575:45"/>have never another to go to. If Chriſtians were in as dark a caſe, as the Emperor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> was, when dying he cried out, <hi>O my poor ſoul, whither art thou going?</hi> they could be in no rational capacity of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering: But hope aſſures them, that there is another world, where things are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in a different manner then they are here in this:<note place="margin">Duas vitas novit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, una eſt in fide alterain ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, una in tempore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terain aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate, una in labore, altera in requie; una cum hoſte pugnat, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera ſine hoſte reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,
<hi>Aug. in Joh. Tract. 124.</hi>
               </note> Here good men bear the Croſs, there they wear the Crown; here they are black with reproaches, there they ſhine as the Sun; here they are toſſed at Sea, there they enter into reſt; here they drink of the bitter Cup, there of the Rivers of Pleaſures above; here they are in the bloody hands of men, there in the arms of a gratious God: Hope is ſure, that theſe things are ſo; God's Promiſes ſecure them, and, that we might have ſtrong conſolation, God's Oaths is ſuperad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo: Our Saviour hath ſealed up the truth of them with his own blood, and we may venter our deareſt lives upon them. Hence it is, that <hi>hope is</hi> ſaid to be <hi>the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of the ſoul, ſure and ſtedfaſt, entring into that within the Vail. Hebr.</hi> 6.19. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Anchors may break, but this will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail; other Anchors are faſtned in this World, but this enters into that within the Vail, and fixes it ſelf in the unmoveable Heaven; and in reſpect thereof, Chriſtians
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60575:45"/>become in ſome meaſure unmovable in the midſt of all the ſtorms here below. St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> ſaith of the Chriſtians in his time, that their Faith and Hope did ſtand unmov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and unſhaken <hi>inter ipſas ſeculi ruinas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trianum.</note> among the ruins of the World. When the excellent
<hi>Melancton</hi> was threatned by his enemies,<note place="margin">Mel. Ad. in vità ejus.</note> that they would not leave him a footſtep in
<hi>Germany,</hi> he replied, <hi>That he ſhould have one in Heaven:</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner when a poor perſecuted Chriſtian is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be caſt out of this World, he may comfort himſelf with this, that he hath another to go to, where he ſhall have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſage: and a reward for his ſufferings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hope aſſures us, that the good things of the World to come do incomparably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the things of this World. If the things of this world were the better, no man would leave better for worſe; nay, if they were but equal, no man would part with that in poſſeſſion for that in expectation; But Hope aſſures us, that the good things of the World to come do far tranſcend thoſe that are in this World: The <hi>manſions in glory</hi> are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the <hi>houſes of clay; the incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inheritance</hi> exceeds a <hi>fading</hi> one; <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Life is much more pretious then <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral;</hi> the <hi>crowns of immortality</hi> above out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine all the <hi>titles of honor</hi> here below; the pure <hi>rivers of Pleaſure</hi> in Heaven are
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60575:46"/>far ſweeter then the <hi>delights</hi> on earth; the <hi>fruiton of God</hi> (who is the <hi>ſupream Good, Center of Souls, Sabbath of rest,</hi> and <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of bleſſedneſs</hi>) cannot but be infinitely beyond the <hi>enjoyment of Creatures.</hi> A good aſſurance, that theſe things are ſo, will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us, to part with the leſſer concerns here below, that we may enjoy the greater that are above. We read of ſome Worthies, that <hi>took joyfully the ſpoiling of their goods,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had <hi>in Heaven a better &amp; endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſubſtance, Hebr.</hi> 10.34. And again, of ſome, that would <hi>not accept deliverance,</hi> becauſe they would <hi>obtain a better reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Heb.</hi> 11.35. Suadows &amp; trifles were to be parted with, rather then Maſiy &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Felicity; the bubble or vapor of a tranſitory Life was to be let go, rather then an everlaſting one. When in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> the Martyrs were asked,
<hi>What made them bear ſuch torments;</hi> and <hi>what they expected after all their ſufferings?</hi> They made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>That they did hope for thoſe good things, which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, which God hath prepared for them that Love him.</hi> We ſee what bore up their ſpirits in their ſufferings; Let us labour to have an high ſenſe of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of the World to come, that, if need
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60575:46"/>be, we may part with all for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hope aſſures our intereſt in the good things of the World to come: And here two things are to be noted; the one is this, Hope in its initial Exiſtence aſſures our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in them fundamentally; he that hath a true lively hope of them, hath a real in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in them; every right Grace touches upon Heaven, and gives a right to it; but Hope doth it in a kind of peculiar way; it enters in within the Vail, and in a ſort takes poſſeſſion of the other World: As the ſhip is at Land in its Anchor, ſo the Soul is in Heaven in its Hope; and he that hath a true intereſt there, will not part with it in a time of ſuffering: The Anchor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Heaven, and faſtned in the unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able felicity there, will hold out in a Storm: Such an one will reckon, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, that <hi>the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which ſhall be revealed in us, Rom.</hi> 8.18. Or, if a compariſon be made, the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in reſpect of the Glory, will be but as a drop of wormwood, to a vaſt Sea of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Sweetneſs. The other thing is this; Hope in its full ſtature aſſures our intereſt in the good things to come ſenſibly; he that hath a plerophory of Hope, certainly knows that he hath an intereſt in them; <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60575:47"/>to Life,</hi> ſaith Sr. <hi>John,</hi> 1,
<hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14. As if the Apoſtle had ſaid, we are in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Heaven, and we know it as it were ſenſibly, as we do our paſſage from one place to another. Holy <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth;</hi> and, maugre all the Worms, <hi>in my Fleſh I ſhall ſee God, Job.</hi> 19.25, 26. He was ſure of the bliſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making Viſion, and could look through the duſt to Immortality: Such a full hope uſhers in a kind of Paradiſe into the Soul, and admirably fits it to bear ſufferings; the internal Suavity is able to ſweeten any outward Condition. The Learned
<hi>Rivet,</hi> at his dying hour, brake forth into theſe words, <hi>Expecto, credo, perſevero, dimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veri nequeo, Dei Spiritus meo Spiritui teſtatur, me eſſe ex Filiis ſuis, O amorem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effabilem!</hi> I expect, believe, perſevere, cannot be moved; Gods Spirit witneſſes to mine, that I am one of his Children; O! ineffable Love! Let us Labor to have, not only a lively hope, that we may have a title to Heaven, but a full hope, that we may know our title to it: This will be an high Cordial in an evil day, and make us able, whatever the ſufferings be, to go on triumphantly and with full Sails to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hope doth not only aſſure the good things to come, but diſpoſes us for them:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60575:47"/>Hope is not an idle Dream or Notion, but it is an active and lively thing; it doth not meerly look to the glory above, but puts the Soul into a poſture for it: Every one, that hath in him the hope of ſo great a thing as the ſeeing the bleſſed God is, <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth himſelf, even as he is pure,</hi> 1, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. He knows Darkneſs cannot have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Light; unclean eyes cannot be opened in ſo pure a place as Heaven is; the earthly heart is too groſs to be in the Region of holy Spirits; he that drowns himſelf in Senſual Pleaſures, is not meet to drink of the pure Rivers that are above: Malitious Spirits cannot be capable of dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there, wher infinite Love opens it ſelf in all its ſweetneſs: The falſe-hearted Hypocrite can never be admitted to ſee Truth in the Original, nor the evil man to drink Goodneſs at the Fountain-head: He therefore that hath a right hope of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with God in Heaven, will purifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for ſuch an high eſtate; he will labor to have more of the light of Faith to fit him for that of Viſion; to have more purity of heart, to make him meet to ſee the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly One; to have more of Heaven in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, to prepare him for that bleſſed Region; to have more ſpiritual delight here, that he may be capable of entring into the joy of his Lord hereafter; to have his heart
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60575:48"/>more filled with holy Love, that he may be in an apt poſture for the rich effuſions of Love in Heaven; to have more truth and goodneſs in his heart, that he may be the more ready to enjoy the Fountain and Fulneſs of both, I mean, the bleſſed God who is <hi>All in All:</hi> Thus this lively Hope makes a man meet for Heaven, and in ſo doing it makes him meet for thoſe Sufferings that lie in his way thither: That Purity, which diſpoſes him to enjoy God in Heaven, doth alſo diſpoſe him to ſuffer for him on Earth; and the greater diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to Heaven, the Center of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the ſtronger will the motion be to break through all difficulties that are in the paſſage thereunto: Let us therefore get a purilying Hope, that we may be fit for the Croſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hope doth not only diſpoſe us for the good things to come, but it waits for them unto the end. Hope is a waiting grace, it makes a Chriſtians life to be a perpetual waiting: <hi>All the days of my appointed time will I wait till my change come,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 14. Verſ. 14. <hi>Job</hi> had many changes, but he waited for that great one, which ſhould bring him into a ſtate of unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale happineſs. Whatever holy men are a doing ſtill they are in a waiting poſture: When
<hi>Jacob</hi> was bleſſing his Sons, he did
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60575:48"/>not for get this, but broke out in a Sudden ſweet Ejaculation, <hi>I have waited for thy Salvation, O Lord, Gen.</hi>
49.18. Hope makes Chriſtians to wait for the good things to come at all times, but in a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner in time of Sufferings: St <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking firſt of the ſuffering Saints, and then of the groaning World, Expreſſeth himſelf thus; We our ſelves alſo, which have the Firſt-fruits of the Spirit, groan within our ſelves, waiting for the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Redemption of our Body, for we are ſaved by Hope,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23, 24. Here we may obſerve the true ſtate and poſture of the Saints; Afflictions make then groan, but the Divine Hope, the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruits of the Spirit, make them wait for a better World, in which Adoption and Redemption ſhall have their compleat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: A Chriſſtian in Afflictions being tormented in this World, will wait for a better. The Martyr <hi>Agatha,</hi> having her Breaſts cruelly cut off for Religion, told the perſecutor, <hi>That yet ſhe had two breaſts remaining, ſuch as he could not touch; the one of Faith, the other of Hope;</hi> which afforded her great Comforts in her Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Faith adheres to the Promiſe, Hope waits for the good things promiſed; both ſtrengthen in a day of Trial: It is the very nature of Divine Hope, to wait for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60575:49"/>the good things to come: When the Sun of Proſperity Shines, it waits in a way of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; <hi>Lord, I have hoped for thy ſalvation, and do thy Commandments,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.166. He waited in a way of obedience to Gods Commands. And when the ſtorm of Perfecution comes, it waits in a way of Patience. Hence the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>patience of hope:</hi> 1.
<hi>Theſſal.</hi> 1.3. That hope, which in Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity waited in a way of Obedience, will in Adverſity wait in a way of Patience: Hope would have the Chriſtian to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways waiting for the upper World, but when the Croſs comes, it preſſeth upon him more vehemently, and will ſpeak af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner to him; <hi>what, haſt thou waited for the great reward in Heaven in Duties and Ordinances, and wilt thou not wait for it in Sufferings too? Heaven is the ſame ſtill, and Sufferings are not worthy to be compared with it:</hi> Do but ſuffer a little, and thou ſhalt be there. When the Martyr
<hi>Ananias,</hi> in the Perſian Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, ſeemed to tremble at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Croſs, <hi>Puſices</hi> ſpake thus to him,<note place="margin">Sozom. L. 2. cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Pauliſper, O ſenex oculos, claude, nam ſtatim lumen Dei videbis;</hi> Shut thine eyes a little, <hi>O old man,</hi> and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou ſhalt ſee the light of God. Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is that of the Apoſtle: <hi>Our light Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60575:49"/>which is but for a moment, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory, while we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal;</hi>
2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18. Here it is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Affliction is light and momentary, but glory is a weight and eternal, there is no proportion between them: If by hope we look at the inviſible and eternal things, this will ſupport our hearts, that it is but a little ſhort ſuffering, and we ſhall be in Heavenly bliſs for ever: Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labor after a waiting hope, that we may patiently bear the Croſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60575:50"/>
            <head>CHAP. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The Seventh Direction for Suffering is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fear; not the Fear of man, but of God; not a diffidential Fear, but a fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial one; not a ſervile Fear, but a filial one: Holy Fear looks at Sin more then at ſuffering; at Sufferings in Hell more then at thoſe on Earth; at Spiritual and Eternal loſſes more then at Carnal and Temporal.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe Seventh Direction is this, if we would be in a fit poſture for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we muſt get an holy Fear in our hearts. The wiſe
<hi>Solomon</hi> begins his <hi>Proverbs</hi> with this; <hi>The fear of the Lord is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> or head <hi>of Knowledge, Prov</hi> 1.7. and ends his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> with this, <hi>That to fear God and keep his Commandments is the whole duty of Man, Eccl.</hi> 12.13. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things appertain to the Beaſt or the Devil, but holy Fear is the All of man; it makes him a perfect man, not only to do Gods Will, but to ſuffer under it. In ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this I ſhall firſt conſider what that Fear is which prepares us for Suffering, and then how it prepares us thereunto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall conſider what that Fear is which prepares us for Suffering; and this
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60575:50"/>I ſhall diſpatch in three things.</p>
            <p>It is not the Fear of man but of God that doth it: It is not the fear of man, that can do it; God gives us a charge againſt this, <hi>Who art thou that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of a man that ſhall dye? Eſay.</hi>
51.12. There is no cauſe to fear a weak piece of Clay, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Breath, a fading Leaf; he muſt dye and there is an end of him, and all his thoughts periſh with him. The wiſe man tels us, <hi>That the fear of man bringeth a Snare, Prov.</hi> 29.25. It made <hi>Abraham</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble as if he had no wife; <hi>David</hi> change his behaviour as if he had no reaſon;
<hi>Peter</hi> curſe and ſwear as if he knew not his Maſter: This Fear diſpoſes to apoſtacy, and muſt be cured by that Fear of God, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to ſuffering: When we are ready to drown in worldly ſorrow, it is of ſingular uſe to ſpring another, a godly ſorrow in our hearts; and when the Fear of man puts us into trembling fits, it is an excellent remedy to raiſe up the Fear of God in our Souls above the other. Thus God directs his People not to fear the confederate Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but to <hi>ſanctify the Lord of Hoſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to let him be</hi> their <hi>fear and</hi> their
<hi>dread, Eſa.</hi> 8.12, 13. He is <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> God over all, and the fear of him ſhould be above all other fears; this is the way to have him to <hi>be a Sanctuary</hi> to us, as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60575:51"/>If we Fear him he will be an inviolable place of retreat where we may repoſe our ſelves in a day of Trouble.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not a diffidential Fear, but a fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial one that doth it: A diffidential Fear makes the mind, as Meteors in the Air, to hang in ſuſpenſe, and, in caſe Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on come, to fail under the burden. St.
<hi>Peter walked upon the water to go to je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; but when he ſaw the wind boiſtrous, he was afraid, and began to ſink, Math.</hi> 14.29, 30. By Faith he walked, and by diffidence he began to ſink.<note place="margin">Non ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laret, niſi crederet nec mergeretur niſi dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taret. <hi>Auſt. de Verbis Rom. Serm. 14.</hi>
               </note> Our conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the very ſame; in the waves of a troubleſome World we ſtand by Faith, but fall by diffidence; That Fear, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares us for ſuffering, muſt be a fiducial one. <hi>Ye that fear the Lord, truſt in the Lord, he is their help and their ſhield, Pſal.</hi> 115.11. Holy fear is and muſt be in Conjunction with faith. Fear flies from the evils of Sin and Hell; Faith cloſes in with the Promiſes of Grace and Glory, both concurr to make a man fit for ſuffering; and ſuch a ſufferer ſhall have God for his help and ſhield.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not a ſervile Fear, but a filial one that doth it: He that hath a meer ſervile fear of the wrath to come, may forbear an act of ſin; but he hath the Love of it in his heart, <hi>adbuc vivit in eo peccandi volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60575:51"/>the Love of ſin lives in him ſtill, as an Ancient hath it. Such an one is not in a fit caſe to ſuffer for the Truth; he hath not a Love to God to move him to it, nor a capacity to have Heaven after it; and how can he ſuffer? It is very hard for a man to ſuffer for a God that he Loves not: Or part with the good things of This World, when he hath no hope of thoſe in a better. That Fear, which prepares for Suffering, is not ſervile, but filial; it ſtands not in conjunction with the love of Sin, but with the Love of God; the nature of it is ſuch, that he that hath it will diſpleaſe man rather then offend God; part with a World rather then let go the Truth and pure Worſhip; nay, and lay down his Life rather then forfeit the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Preſence and Favour which are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Life. Thus much touching the nature of that Fear, which prepares us for ſuffering.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I come to conſider how holy Fear doth prepare us for ſufferings; and this I ſhall open in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Holy fear looks upon ſin as an evil much greater then any ſuffering: ſuffering is oppoſite to the Creature, but ſin is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the infinite God; it is a Rebellion to his Soveraignty, a contradiction to his Holineſs, a provocation to his Juſtice; an
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60575:52"/>abuſe to his Grace; a ſtain caſt, as much as in us, lies, upon his Glory; nay, as the Schools ſpeak, it is a kind of
<hi>Deicidium,</hi> it ſtrikes in a ſort at the very life and being of God; it wiſhes, that there were none at all; and, if it could effect it, there ſhould be none: Suffering doth not make a man worſe then he was before, but ſin doth it: Thoſe Saints that were deſtitute, afflicted, tormented, wandring in Deſerts, and Mountains, and Dens and Caves of the Earth, were yet ſuch excellent ones, that <hi>the World was not worthy</hi> of them,
<hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.37, 38. On the other hand, <hi>Antiochus Ephiphanes</hi> (who was, as his name im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, illuſtrious and glorious in the World) was yet but a vile perſon, and was made ſuch by his wickedneſs. Suffering ſtrikes at the eſtate or body of man, but ſin ſtrikes at his Soul, a thing more pretious then a World; nay, and at the Divine Image there, which is more worth then the Soul it ſelf: It doth, where it can prevail, turn men into Beaſts in its ſenſual luſts, or into Devils in its ſpiritual Wickedneſſes: Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may have good, nay great good in it, but ſin is evil, only evil; tis called by St. <hi>James</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the
<hi>ſuperfluity</hi> or <hi>excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all evil, Jam.</hi> 1.21. It contains all evils in it; and if all evils (ſaith a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Divine) were to have a ſcum or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60575:52"/>crement, ſin is it, as being the abſtracted quinteſſence of all evil, and having nothing at all of good in it. Sin, ſaith <hi>Bradwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi> is a thing not to be done, <hi>pro quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſcunque bonis lucrandis, aut pro quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſcunque malis praecavendis;</hi> for the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never ſo great a good, or for the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never ſo great an evil. He that hath this holy Fear in his heart, will chuſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering as the leſſer evil, rather then ſin, which is much the greater. When <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus Epiphanes</hi> brought forth Wheels, Rodds, Hooks, Rakes, Racks, Caudrons,<note place="margin">Joſeph. Ant.</note> Cages, Gridirons, Gantlets, Awles, Bellows, Braſen Pots, and Frying-pans, before <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamona</hi> &amp; here ſeven ſons to terrify them, they could not be induced by all his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Engines to treſpaſs ſo far as to eat of a little ſacrificed Swines-fleſh, to ſave themſelves from a cruel death. It was the ſaying of <hi>Anſelm, That if Sin were ſet before him on one hand, and Hell on the other, he would rather chuſe Hell then ſin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scult. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad. An. Dom. <hi>1528</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Henry Flander,</hi> being a Priſoner for the Proteſtant Religion, would not ſay, that his Wife was his Whore, no, not to ſave his life offered to him on thoſe terms. Holy Fear will tell us, that ſin muſt not be done to avoid ſuffering; that we were better bear all reproaches then dishonour God; loſe our Eſtates then leave our Religion;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60575:53"/>nay, and lay down our lives then be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Divine Love. O let us look upon ſin as the <hi>Maximum formidabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le;</hi> as that which hath in it the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſe of fear and flight, that no exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal miſeries and dangers may be able to drive us into it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Holy Fear looks at the ſufferings which God inflicts in Hell, as incomparably great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then thoſe which man doth or can inflict upon Earth. Our Saviour directing our fear to its right Object, takes notice of the vaſt difference between them, <hi>Fear not them, which kill the body, but are not able to kill he ſoul; but rather fear him, which is able to deſtroy both ſoul and body in</hi> Hell, <hi>Math.</hi> 10.28. Mans killing is one thing, but Gods deſtroying another: Man may kill the Body, and it may be in a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting manner; but there is no death like the ſecond; no torments on Earth are comparable to thoſe in Hell; no finite arm can ſtrike ſo hard as the infinite One; no Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linary or Elementary Fire can burn ſo hot as the Infernal doth. God bid <hi>Moſes take and ſprinkle the aſhes of the Furnace, and they ſhould become boils and blains, Exod.</hi> 9.8, 9. A Great Doctor of ours gloſſes on the words thus; <hi>The ſufferings here on Earth are but the aſhes of the Furnace, ſmall things in compariſon of the Furnace itſelf;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60575:53"/>an Hell of unquenchable fire; man may kill the body, but he is not alwaies a killing of it; he may torment, but he cannot bear up the Patient in long ſuffering; the torments in a little time will ceaſe, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Sleep in Jeſus; but God kils the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and is ſtill a killing them, power ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports them, and Juſtice puniſhes them; the fire of Hell, kindled by eternal breath, never goes out, and the ſmoak of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſcends for ever and ever: After thouſands, and ten thouſand of years, ſtill there will be wrath to come, ſuch as no time can meaſure: Man may kill the body, but after that he can do no more,</hi> his <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines of Cruelty cannot reach the Soul, or touch the inward man, which is a Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary for God; but God kils the ſoul, his wrath is in a peculiar manner poured out there where the chief ſeat of ſin was; the neverdying Worm is ever growing upon cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: The ſpirit of the damned furiouſly reflects upon itſelf over the eternal miſery that it lies under: All the horrors of a</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra <hi>or a</hi> Judas <hi>are far ſhort of that deſperate rage and anguiſh which tortures the loſt ſouls in Hell.</hi> He that hath this holy fear in him will chuſe any ſufferings on Earth rather then thoſe in Hell. One of the ſons of <hi>Solomona</hi> told the Tyrant <hi>Antiochus,</hi> that his fire was cold, and indeed it was ſo
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60575:54"/>comparatively to the Fire of Hell: St.
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> putting the queſtion, whom we ſhould obey; God commanding one thing or the Emperor commanding another, makes his anſwer;
<hi>Da veniam, Imperator, tu car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerem minaris, ille gehennam,</hi> Gives place, O Emperor,<note place="margin">De Verb. Dom. ſerm. 6.</note> thou threatneſt a Priſon, he a Hell. When <hi>Polycarp</hi> was threatned with Fire, his anſwer was, <hi>That the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter threatned only a momentary Fire, but knew not The Eternal one.</hi> He, that ever heard that true Thunder, which is the voice of God, <hi>would hardly be afraid of ſuch</hi> Artificial Cracks as the Emperor <hi>Cajus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula</hi> uſed to make to ſhew himſelf a God: And he that carries upon his heart an awe of thoſe ſufferings which God inflicts in Hell, will hardly fear thoſe which men inflict on Earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Holy Fear looks upon Spiritual and Eternal Loſſes, as incomparably greater then Carnal and Temporal ones: The loſs of the World may be made up in the ſaving of the Soul; but for the loſs of a Soul, nothing can make a recompence: That little ſparkle of Divinity mightily outweighs the great Globe of the World: What are Bodies to Spirits? <hi>Nemo</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>bene ſe inſpex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, qui non omni corpori qualemlibet ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam praeponendam eſſe fateatur;</hi> he that looks well into himſelf muſt confeſs, that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60575:54"/>any Soul is to be preferred before all Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. The loſs of mans favor may be rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made up by the preſence of Gods.
<hi>Moſes</hi> endured the King's wrath, as ſeeing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible one; the preſence of God was ſo with him, that he feared no human frowns: But if the Divine Favour be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, nothing can ſupply the defect of it. It's true, a man without it may have all outward bleſſings flowing round about him; but he eats, and drinks, and Sleeps, under the wrath of God, which hangs over his head, as the ſword did over the head of <hi>Damocles</hi> at the Tyrants Table; and, as ſoon as the thread of life breaks, it comes down upon him in an utter ruine. The loſs of Creatures may be made up by an intereſt in God; a real Chriſtian having nothing, may poſſeſs all things in him: but if a man forſake God, what will the World give in exchang for him? It's Riches are but poor moth-eaten things, which in a little time vaniſh away; its Pleaſures are but the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillations of Senſe, and periſh in the uſing; its Honours are but a blaſt, a little popular Air, which ſoon go away and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. When once God, who is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Spring of all good, departs, it is in vain to hope for any thing from the little Rivulets and Ciſterns of the Creature. He, that hath this holy Fear in him, will chuſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60575:55"/>to ſuffer loſs in Carnal and Temporal things, rather then in Spiritual and Eternal. It is the ſaying of St.
<hi>Ambroſe, Eaeſt vera pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etas, quaepraeponit divina humanis, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petua temporalibus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 7. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 56.</note> that is, true Piety, which prefers Divine Things to humane, and perpetual things to temporal. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſets out ſervile and filial Fear by an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and a Chaſt Wife; <hi>Timet mulier adultera,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Joh. Tract. 63. in E piſt. Joh. Tract. 9.</note> 
               <hi>ne vir ejus veniat; timet &amp; caſta ne vir ejus abſcedat:</hi> The adulterous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſears, leſt her husband may come; the chaſt woman fears leſt her husband depart. In like manner ſervile Fear makes us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid that God will puniſh, &amp; filial Fear makes us afraid that God will depart: The loſs of him is more then the loſs of all things. When the Martyr <hi>Menas,</hi> under the Perſecution of <hi>Diocleſian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magd. hiſt Cent 4. cap. 12.</note> was brought forth to ſuffer, he gave this reaſon for it;
<hi>Nihileſt, quod meâ ſententiá conferripoſſit cum regno coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum; neque enim totus Mundus poteſt, aequâ lance expenſus uni comparari animae;</hi> there is nothing in my judgment like the Kingdom of Heaven; neither may the whole World, if weighed in an equal bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, be compared with one Soul. He had rather loſe any thing in the World then an Heaven and a Soul. O let us labour to know where the great loſs lies, that we may never forſake Spiritual and Eternal things for Carnal and Temporal.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60575:55"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The eighth Direction for Sufferings is Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. A high Fabrick muſt have a low foundation. Humility hath ſuch rays from God, as makes us very low in our own eyes: It is a Capacity for larger Effuſions of Grace; it ſubjects a man to to all the pleaſures of God; it cauſes him to depend upon God for ſupport and comfort.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe eighth Direction is this, if we would be in a fit poſture for Suffering, we muſt labour after humility of mind. It is the direction of our Saviour to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Verb. Do n.ſer. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Math.</hi>
11.29. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> upon thoſe words gives an excellent Rule;
<hi>Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas magnam fabricam conſtruere celſitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, de fundamento prius cogita humilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> Thou thinkeſt to build a great high Fabrick, but firſt think to make a low Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: The higher the Building is, the lower muſt be the Foundation. If we would build our Chriſtianity as high as Suffering for Religion, we had need lay a deep Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in Humility for it. Our Saviour Chriſt was not only a Pattern of Suffering, but of Humility too: St. <hi>Peter</hi> tels us, that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60575:56"/>
               <hi>he ſuffered, leaving us an example,</hi>
2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, how he came to Suffer; he emptied himſelf, or made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of no Reputation, <hi>he humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, the death of the Groſs. Phil.</hi>
2.7, 8. He laid by his Robes of Majeſty, and became, as it were, nothing, that he might ſuffer for us: If we would follow Chriſt in Suffering, we muſt put off our Ornaments, and lay by our proud Plumes; we muſt empty our ſelves of all our Self-excellencies, and become vile; <hi>yea, nothing</hi> in our own eyes, that we may endure the trial.<note place="margin">Ex Saulo factus eſt Paulus, ex ſuperbo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus: Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum enim modicum eſt.
<hi>Auſt. in Pſal. 72.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a great Sufferer For Chriſt, but withal he was one of the humbleſt that ever lived: Indeed before his Converſion he was a <hi>Saul,</hi> a proud Perſecutor; but after it he was a <hi>Paul,</hi> perſecuted, and little in his own eyes.
<hi>Athanaſius,</hi> who ſuffered ſo much under the <hi>Arians,</hi> had this Character given him by <hi>Nazianzen, That he was high in worth, and humble in heart.</hi> There are four things to be noted in Humility; each of which tend to prepare us for Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Humility dwels in an enlightned mind, &amp; hath ſuch rayes from God, as make the heart where it is, take up very low thoughts of itſelf. Of old the appearances of God in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Symbols of Glory, made men lye very
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60575:56"/>low before him. When <hi>Job</hi> heard the voice of the Lord out of the whirl-wind, <hi>he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred himſelf in duſt and aſhes, Iob</hi> 42. 6. When the Prophet ſaw the Lord <hi>ſitting upon a throne</hi> high and lifted up, he cried out. <hi>Woe is me, I am undone, Eſay.</hi> 6.5. When <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw the Viſion of the <hi>bright ſhining man,</hi> his <hi>comelineſs was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to corruption, Dan.</hi>
10.8. The noble man now hath not ſuch outward appearances, but he hath an inward light of faith, and when he looks up to God, and reflects upon himſelf, it makes him go <hi>in fundum,</hi> into the Center of the Earth, and there to ſee his own nothingneſs. I ſhall give a triple inſtance of this: When the humble man looks up to the glory and greatneſs of God, he reflects and communes with his Heart after this manner, O how high is God! his
<hi>glory is above the Heavens,</hi> his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> is <hi>infinitely brighter then a thouſand ſuns,</hi> the rayes of it bid me go down and hide my ſelf in the duſt of my own vileneſs and nothingneſs; how great is he, that <hi>ſpans the Heavens, weighs the mountains,</hi> and <hi>meaſures the Seas in the hollow of his hand?</hi> To him all Nations are but as a
<hi>drop of the bucket,</hi> a <hi>duſt of the Ballance;</hi> nay, leſs then nothing itſelf: And I, what am I? the drop of a drop, a piece of a duſt, and much leſs then that which is leſs then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60575:57"/>itſelf. Such thoughts as theſe do ſo abaſe and annihilate a man in his ſenſe, that the great and glorious God may do any thing with him; his own littleneſs will keep him from murmuring under any Croſs or Affliction that comes from the moſt High. Again when the humble man looks to the holineſs of God, he ſpeaks to his heart: God is very holy, he is perfect pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity without any ſpot, infinite light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any darkneſs at all; the glance of his pure eyes bids me go down into my Spotted ſelf, and there cover my ſelf with the ſhame of that Corruption, that is worſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: The <hi>Stars are not pure in his ſight,</hi> and how can I be ſo? The glorious <hi>Angels cover their faces, and cry to him, holy, holy, holy;</hi> and what ſhould Worms do! What reaſon have I to cry out over my ſelf, as the Leper was to do, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean.</hi> The ſenſe of this is ſo deeply humbling, that it diſpoſes him that hath it to be willing to go into any Furnace, which God orders for the melting out of his Droſs. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Martyr Mr. <hi>Hooper,</hi> carried his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility with him to the Fiery Trial, there he prayed thus; <hi>Lord I am Hell, but thou art Heaven; I am a Sink of Sin, but thou art a gracious Redeemer:</hi> The ſenſe of his own imperfections made him lye very Low. Moreover, when the humble man looks
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60575:57"/>to the Grace of God, he adores that pure ſelf-moving Fountain of all Good; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, abaſes himſelf under his great unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of the Leaſt drop of it: <hi>The evil that is in me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is my own, but all the good that is in me is entirely from Grace.</hi> This taſt of Grace to a mans unworthy ſelf, admirably diſpoſes him to bear the Croſs: Such an one will argue with himſelf, Shall God give me Grace and Glory, and ſhall I not ſuffer for him? The ſuffering is not the Hell I deſerve, but that which is much leſs, and ſhall I not ſuffer? There is a glorious Heaven to come after it, and why ſhould I hang back?<note place="margin">Expoſit. on the Theſſal.</note> The words of Doctor <hi>Sclater</hi> are very remarkable, God (ſaith he) rewards <hi>ultra condignum,</hi> afflicts <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra condignum;</hi> that Perſwaſion who ſo carries, and is acquainted with his foul ſins, willingly prays with <hi>Auſtin, Hîc ure, hîc ſeca, ut in aeternum parcas;</hi> here burn, here cut me, that thou maieſt ſpare for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Thus humility, by the rayes that it hath from God, makes a man very vile in his own eyes, and ſo prepares him for the Croſs. The proud man, that thinks highly of himſelf, will murmure at any thing; and the humble man that thinks meanly of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will bear with any thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Humility puts the Soul into a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to have larger effuſions of Grace beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon it; <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, but
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60575:58"/>giveth grace unto the humble, Jam.</hi> 4.6. God hath two hands; with the one, he caſts down the proud that lift up themſelves againſt him; with the other, he lifts up the humble, that lye at his feet for mercy. Humility is not only a Grace, but a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to receive more of it. He, that goes to a River to take up water, puts the mouth of his Veſſel downward to do it; he that goes to God for Grace, muſt put his mouth in the duſt, and cry to have it, not for his worths ſake, but for his ſpiritual poverty. An humble Heart is (as <hi>Pariſienſis cals it</hi>) a ſpiritual <hi>Vacuum;</hi> and as nature doth not ſuffer a <hi>Vacuum</hi> in Bodies, but fils up the ſpace one way or other, ſo Grace doth not ſuffer a <hi>Vacuum</hi> in Spirits, but fils up the humble Soul with freſh ſupplies of Grace. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſets out this by a notable ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,<note place="margin">Si humiles ſunt, valles ſunt, quod infuderis capiunt, non dimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt. <hi>Auſt. de Verb. Apoſt. ſer.
9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The water that fals down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon the Mountains, flows away, but the water that fals upon the Vallys, ſtays there;</hi> In like manner the Divine Grace, that diſtils from above, doth not reſt upon high proud perſons, but upon humble ones: God leaves the full Souls, and fils the emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; abaſes the exalted, and exalts the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed: All other Graces grow together with Humility; the more humble we are, the more we have of God with us, the more we have of Grace in us; and the more
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60575:58"/>we have of theſe, the more we have of ſtrength in the inner man, and the more we have of preparation for a day of Trial. If we build ſo high as ſuffering for Chriſt, we muſt dig deep, and lay the Foundation low; that, when the ſtorm comes, we may ſtand faſt and unmovable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Humility makes a man freely to bow and ſubject himſelf to God in all things: This is a choice and excellent preparative for ſuffering; the ſame which our Saviour commends to <hi>weary and heavy laden ſouls; take my yoke upon you; and learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart, Math.</hi> 11.29. Chriſtians are to take up a double yoke, the yoke of Evangelical Commands, and the yoke of the Croſs that accompanies them; in both ſubjection is requiſite; In the one, Subjection to Chriſts Authority commanding; in the other, ſubjection to his Providence ordering: And that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may be ſubject to both, they muſt look to the great Pattern, &amp; learn meekneſs and humility from him. The heart of man naturally is a very proud <hi>Belial</hi> thing, that will bear no yokes, it will not be under Chriſt; not under his Righteous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands by Obedience; nor under his Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Providences by Patience; it lifts up itſel, and by a kind of Blaſphemy practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callſ aſpires to be above God himſelf: But
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60575:59"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:60575:59"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:60575:60"/>when the Divine Grace hath melted the heart and made it humble, then it will bow down and take both yokes upon itſelf; it will become freely ſubject to God and all his holy pleaſure. I ſay, freely: A proud man may be bowed down under the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of an external Calamity, but an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man bows himſelf down by an internal Principle of Grace; in the one, the ſubjection is meerly of neceſſity, in the other it is free and of choice. Humility makes a man lye at Gods foot, and ſay,
<hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> or What wilt thou have me to ſuffer? <hi>Let the word of God come</hi> (ſaith <hi>Baldaſſer</hi> the
<hi>German</hi> Divine) <hi>and we will ſubmit to it ſix hundred necks, if we had ſo many.</hi> Let the Croſs come (ſaith the humble man) and I will ſubmit to it: Humility is virtually all obedience and patience, it makes a man to be as a little child, ruleable by all the Will of God: Whether that Will come forth in Precepts or providences, Humility will comply and bow down under it: The lowly in heart will do, or be any thing for God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour promiſes reſt to ſuch,<note place="margin">De Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Ser. 213.</note> as the gracious reward of their labors and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. It is good counſel that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> gives, <hi>Eſto parvus in oculis tuis, ut ſis magnus in oculis Dei;</hi> be thou little in thine own eyes, that thou mayſt be great
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60575:60"/>in Gods; Subjecting thy ſelf to all his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is the way to be exalted by him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Humility cauſes a man to depend upon God for ſupport and comfort in his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. The proud perſon ſtands in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of the Phariſee, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelf, Luk.</hi> 18.11. he ſtands upon his own bottom, and thinks himſelf able by his own power to do or ſuffer any thing as he pleaſes: But ſtanding in his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, it is very likely that he will fall off as ſoon as the trial comes. But it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with the humble man; he knows that he is weak in himſelf, and muſt be ſtrong in God, and therefore he will not truſt in his own Power or Will, but look up to God for ſupport and comfort in the evil day.<note place="margin">De Verb. Dom. ſer. 13.</note> It is a notable paſſage of St <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, Multos impedit a firmitate praeſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio firmitatis, nemo a Deo fit firmus, niſi qui a ſeipſo ſentit infirmum:</hi> A preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of firmneſs hinders many from being firm; no man is made firm by God, but he that feels infirmity in himſelf. The ſtory in the <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution is very memorable; <hi>Mr.</hi> Sanders <hi>the Martyr at firſt ſhewed much weakneſs and fear, but Dr.</hi> Pendleton <hi>ſaid to him, What man! fear? I will ſee every drop of my greaſe mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before I forſake Christ and his truth: But afterwards,</hi> Sanders <hi>triumphantly
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60575:61"/>Suffered, kiſſing the Stake, and ſaying, Welcome the Croſs of Chriſt; but proud</hi> Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton <hi>turned Papiſt.</hi> Unto this inſtance I ſhall add a more ancient one;
<hi>Peter</hi> a Great Apoſtle fell and denied his Lord; but among the Primitive Chriſtians, Women and little Children ſuffered in a brave and heroical maner.<note place="margin">Auſt. in Joh. tract. 113.</note> The greateſt Chriſtians may fall, by preſuming upon themſelves; the Leaſt may ſtand, by depending on the power of God: The poor in Spirit would not be their own Keepers, but would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves unto God, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
10.14. as being ſafer in his hands then in their own. Humble ſouls, not being able to bear up their own weight, lean upon the Rock of Ages; and, having no reſt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they acquieſce in the Center of Souls. The feeble Conies have their houſes in the Rocks, and the weak Chriſtians dwell in the ſecret of the moſt high. <hi>Annas Burgus,</hi> a Senator of
<hi>Paris,</hi> ſuffered for the pure Religion with that conſtancy, that many were curious to know what Religion that was, for which he ſo patiently endured death; and one reaſon of his patience was his humble dependance upon God, which he expreſſed in that often repeated prayer at his death,
<hi>Deus mi, ne me derelinquas, ne ego te derelinquam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thuan Lib. 23.</note> O my God leave me not, leſt I leave thee: He knew that his
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60575:61"/>ſtrength was in God only. Oh let us labor to have an humble dependance upon God, that, when ſufferings come, we may look and be ſupported, wait and renew ſtrength, be nothing in our ſelves and have all in God: So we ſhall be ſafe and ſecure from anxious fears;
<hi>dabitur in horâ,</hi> ſupport and comfort will come in the time of need.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The ninth Direction for Suffering is Active Obedience to the will of God; it flows from a good and honeſt heart; it reſpects Gods will and Glory; it makes us to grow up into Chriſt, and to be allied to him; it encreaſes Grace and ſpiritual ſtrength; it obtains the gracious Preſence of God, and it is the way to Heaven.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe ninth Direction is this; if we would be in a fit poſture for Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt labor after an Active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Will of God; to do in a right manner as he would have us to do. It is a notable ſaying of the Rabbins, <hi>Marces praeceptum praecepti;</hi> one Precept is the reward of another: He that rightly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves one Precept, ſhall have in the name of a reward ſuch Grace from God, as ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60575:62"/>him to do another and a more difficult Command. It is an excellent thing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure our ſelves to the doing of Gods will; Obedience is the chain about the Spouſes neck, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.9. one link hangs upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; one piece of Obedience draws on another; Active Obedience will prepare us for paſſive; the doing of Gods Will, will diſpoſe us for the Suffering of it. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle prays for the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> firſt, <hi>that they might walk worthy of the Lord, unto all pleaſing, being fruitful in every good work; and then in the next</hi> Verſe, <hi>that they might be ſtrengthned with all might according to his glorious power, unto all patience and long ſuffering with joyfulneſs, Col.</hi> 1.10.11. Where we may obſerve, that an holy Life goes before, and then ſuffering Graces follow after. There are in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſix things obſervable, each of which tend to prepare us for Suffering.</p>
            <p n="1">1. True Obedience flows from a good and an honeſt heart; nay, I may adde, it flows from the holy Spirit of God. It flows from a good and honeſt Heart; many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable hearers that are, but the good and honeſt Heart <hi>brings forth fruit.</hi> It was an high Character which the Apoſtle gives to the <hi>Romans, That they had obeyed from the Heart, that form of doctrine, which was delivered to them,</hi> or (as it is in the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60575:62"/>original) <hi>into which they were delivered, Rom.</hi> 6.17. The Goſpel was not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to them, but they were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and, as it were, caſt into the mould of it, and that was the reaſon that they obeyed from the heart. Nay, further, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience flows from the holy ſpirit; it is a choice Promiſe in the Covenant, <hi>I will put my ſpirit into you, and cauſe you to walk in my ſtatutes, Ezek.</hi> 36.27. Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience being a meer ſupernatural act, comes from the holy Spirit as the prime Cauſe thereof; a general Concourſe ſuffices not, there muſt be a peculiar Motion and Impulſion of the Spirit in it; which made
<hi>Gerſon</hi> ſay, That all ſpiritual life was founded <hi>in miraculo influentiae divinae,</hi> in the miracle of a Divine Influence. We ſee what are the Principles and Fountains of Active Obedience, and the very ſame will produce Paſſive too. <hi>The good and honeſt heart brings forth fruit with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Luke.</hi> 8.15. The words <hi>(with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience)</hi> are very remarkable; the <hi>good and honeſt heart</hi> may meet with Perſecutions in the world, yet it would bloſſome and <hi>bring forth fruit</hi> in the midſt thereof. <hi>The righteous flouriſhes as the Palm-Tree, Pſal.</hi>
92.12. The Palm-Tree is a Symbol of Immortality, growing under its bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and the Righteous, who hath an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60575:63"/>ſeed in him, flouriſhes under all the preſſures of a perſecuting World. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the holy Spirit; which makes good men do Gods will, will enable them to ſuffer it too; St. <hi>Paul</hi> took <hi>pleaſure in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> becauſe when he was
<hi>weak,</hi> then he was <hi>ſtrong,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. that is, the holy Spirit did ſtrengthen his inward man to bear the Croſs. The holy Spirit in the Saints is a <hi>Well of water, ſpringing up to everlaſting Life,</hi> John. 4.14. The perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting World would fain ſtop and damme it up; but in the midſt of all Oppoſitions it Springs, and never leaves ſpringing till the Saints be in Heaven; and before they come thither, it is, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>a ſpirit of glory resting upon them,</hi>
1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. it brings down ſome glimpſes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into their hearts, whilſt they are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. True Obedience hath a pure reſpect to Gods Will and Glory: It hath a pure reſpect to Gods Will; it doth not do the Commands of God upon a by-account, as <hi>Jehu</hi> deſtroied <hi>Ahab's</hi> houſe; but it doth them <hi>intuitu Voluntatis,</hi> becauſe it is the will of God; it is that which ſwaies and caſts the ballance in a good mans heart and life: As in matters of Faith he believes, becauſe God hath ſaid it; ſo in matters of Practiſe he obeys becauſe God hath
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60575:63"/>commanded it. Alſo it hath a pure reſpect to Gods Glory; <hi>Mens cujuſque id eſt quiſque;</hi> the man is as his mind is, and the mind is as his end is; An obedient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will not be a Center to himſelf, nor make God the moſt excellent Being, a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium to any other thing: His great deſign is that God in all things may be glorified: His Holineſs is but to ſhine as a beam from the holy one; his Mercy is but as a little drop flowing from the Divine Ocean; his Obedience is to tell the World that God is ſupream; like his Saviour Chriſt, <hi>he ſeeks not his own glory, but his Fathers.</hi> Such an Obedience as this admirably diſpoſes a man for ſuffering; He, that doth ſome things becauſe they are commanded, will take up the Croſs too, becauſe it is in a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner commanded in the Goſpel: The ſtamp of the Divine Authority is not only found upon the Precepts of Piety and Juſtice, but upon that of Patience too: Alſo, he that doth ſincerely glorify God in other things, will, if occaſion be, glorifie him in pious ſufferings: Some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may be done to God in other Duties, but in no other thing is there ſuch honour given to him as in bearing the Croſs; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a man doth practically declare that he values God above all the World; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Martyrs have (as the School-men
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60575:64"/>tell us) a greater reward in heaven than others: Others have the eſſential Glory in the Viſion of God, but for the Martyrs is reſerved an <hi>Aureola,</hi> a peculiar Coronet to be added to their Crown of Glory, <hi>prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter victoriam de mundo,</hi> for their victory over the World</p>
            <p n="3">3. True Obedience makes us to grow up into Chriſt the Head, and to be of neer alliance to him. It makes us to <hi>grow up into Chriſt the head, Eph.</hi> 4.15. Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, being the exerciſe of all Graces, brings us into a neer union with Chriſt, and makes us more and more like to him: The more we act our Love, Meekneſs, Mercy, Goodneſs or any Grace, the more we are united to him and incorporated with him; nay, true Obedience makes us to be of neer alliance to him. When our Saviour was told, that his Mother and Brethren ſtood without to ſee him, his anſwer was, <hi>My Mother and my Brethren are thoſe which hear the word of God and do it, Luke</hi> 8.20, 21. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon theſe words tels us,<note place="margin">In Lucam. cap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Religioſiores copulae mentium quam corporum;</hi> the conjunction of Minds is more ſacred than that of Bodies. The O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Chriſtian is Brother to Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born of the ſame holy Spirit in Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, of which he was conceived in his Incarnation; nay, he is Mother to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60575:64"/>Chriſt, bringing him forth in the exerciſe of holy Graces; ſomewhat of the Love, Mercy, Piety, Meekneſs of Chriſt is ſtill a coming forth from him: In both theſe reſpects doth obedience diſpoſe us to ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the more we grow up into Chriſt the Head, the more Divine Power and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue we have from him; our chief ſtrength lies not in our ſelves, but in our Head; we may do, nay and ſuffer any thing, through him ſtrengthning us: And the more we are allied to him, the more we are bound to adhere to him: Our ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Birth obliges us to live to him, nay, and if need be, to die for him; and we are to bring him forth not only in other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Virtue, but in that of Patience. St. <hi>Paul</hi> bore about in his body <hi>the dying of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.10. and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of Chriſt muſt be ready at Gods call to ſuffer with him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. True Obedience produces an increaſe of Grace and ſpiritual Strength: Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a Chriſtians daily walk; the more he exerciſes himſelf to Godlineſs, the more grace he hath in his Soul: That Faith, which was but as a little grain of Muſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, becomes a Tree ſpreading itſelf forth at laſt as high as aſſurance: That love, which was as a little ſpark raked up in the aſhes, comes to be a vehement Flame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60575:65"/>after the fruition of God in Heaven: That Hope, which was but a poor weak thing in the Soul, comes to have more livelineſs and ſupernatural ſtature. The path of the juſt, which is in obedience, is as the ſhining light, <hi>which ſhines more and more unto the perfect day in heaven, Prov.</hi> 4.18. The more a Chriſtian exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes himſelf in Obedience, the ſtronger he grows in the Inner-man: of a Plant he comes to be a Tree of Righteouſneſs; of a Babe he comes to be a Man in Chriſt: His vital Principles become more ſtrong, his ſupernatural hear increaſed, he holds on his way of Obedience, and ſo <hi>grows ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and stronger,</hi> Job 17.9. Such an Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience as this admirably Diſpoſes a man for ſuffering: The greater his ſtock of Grace is, the better will he hold out in the ſtraits of the World: The more ſtrength he hath in the inner-man, the more able he will be to bear the burden of the Croſs: <hi>If thou faint in the day of adverſity, thy ſtrength is ſmall,</hi> Prov.
24.10. Great ſtrength will keep a man from fainting. When the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> were come to be above ſix hundred thouſand,
<hi>Numb.</hi> 1.46. it was a great encouragement to make them go on gallantly againſt their Enemies: And when Chriſtians have their Graces multiplied, and among the reſt Patience comes to be <hi>all
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60575:65"/>Patience,</hi> as the expreſſion is,
<hi>Col.</hi> 1.11. it gives them ſpirit and life to bear ſufferings.</p>
            <p n="5">5. True obedience obtains the gracious Preſence of God to help and comfort good men in the doing his Will: The Rabbins ſay, <hi>That if two ſit together conferring about the Law, the</hi> Shechinah <hi>is among them:</hi> I may ſay, if one ſingle Chriſtian be a doing of Gods will, the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is with him: Thus our Saviour ſaith: <hi>If any man love him, and keep his words, the Father and the Son will come and make their abode with ſuch an one,</hi> John 14.23. Such an one hath a
<hi>Shechinah</hi> in his heart; God will be there helping and comforting of him. Whilſt he is a doing of Gods will, ſtrength will come in, as it did to the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.26. and not only ſtrength, but comfort too: <hi>In keeping his commands there is great reward;</hi> ſome of the oyl of Joy, which is upon Chriſt the great doer of Gods will, drops down upon good men in their ſincere obedience; they have an inward peace, and joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable: In this reſpect obedience pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the heart of Chriſtians to endure ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering: An obedient Chriſtian can argue thus with himſelf; I have found Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Preſence ſtrengthning and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me in the doing of his will, much more ſhall I have it when I come to ſuffer,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60575:66"/>and part with all for his ſake. When all forſook St. <hi>Paul,</hi> yet <hi>the Lord ſtood with him, and ſtrengthned him,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.19. When Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> was examined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his Religion, he was wonderfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and received a taſt of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, a pleaſant refreſhing did iſſue from every part of his Body to his heart, and from thence into all parts again.
<hi>Cicely Ormes</hi> was filled with ſuch joy and comfort, that at the kindling of the fire, ſhe ſaid, <hi>My ſoul doth magnify the Lord, and my Spirit doth rejoice in God my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> O let us firmly conclude this with our ſelves, <hi>that God will not leave or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his people,</hi> no not at other times, much leſs will he do it in the time of Fiery Trials: Then they ſhall have ſtrength and comfort in a more than ordinary way, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make them to triumph over their Sufferings, or at leaſtwiſe to bear them with Patience.</p>
            <p n="6">6. True Obedience is the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Thoſe bleſſed ones, that do the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God <hi>have right to the Tree of Life, and enter in through the gates into the City, Rev.</hi> 22.14. The more obedient a man is to the Divine Will, the richer entrance he hath into the bleſſed Kingdom: After ſowing to the Spirit comes the Crop of Eternal Glory; after walking in holy
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60575:66"/>Obedience, comes the bleſſed end of Life and Immortality. In this reſpect Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence fits us for Sufferings: A man that is in the way to Hell, is not capable of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; it is not imaginable that a man ſhould bear Reproach for Chriſt, who hath no hope of Glory; or that he ſhould part with his Treaſure here, who hath none in Heaven; or that he ſhould lay down his Life Temporal, who hath no right to an Eternal one; or that he ſhould let go his Portion of good in this World, who hath none in another. But the Obedient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, who is in the way to Heaven, is in a capacity to ſuffer any thing that meets him in the paſſage thither: Reproaches may come, but he is going to ſhine in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; Worldly Goods may be ſpoiled, but he hath an Inheritance incorruptible that fadeth not away; Temporal Life may be loſt, but in the very inſtant there begins an Eternal one with the bleſſed God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; he may by a Perſecution be juſtled out of this World, but he hath a better to go to, where there are Crowns of Glory, Rivers of Pleaſures, Plenitudes of Joy, and all in the bleſſed God. Our Saviour Chriſt for <hi>the joy that was ſet before him, endured the croſs,</hi> Hebr. 12.2. St. <hi>Paul</hi> would <hi>finiſh</hi> his
<hi>courſe</hi> that he might have the <hi>Crown of righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.7,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60575:67"/>8. When the Martyr <hi>Babylas</hi> ſuffered, he ſung that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. cent. 3. cap. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Return unto thy reſt O my Soul;</hi> his mind was upon the eternal Sabbath in Heaven. When <hi>Baſil</hi> the great was threatned with Baniſhment, and Death, he was not at all moved at it: Baniſhment is nothing to him that hath heaven for his Countrey; neither is Death any thing to one to whom it is the way to Life: He that is in the way to Heaven hath great reaſon to break through all Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to get thither.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The tenth Direction for ſuffering, is Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence under Gods will: With reſpect to the Chriſtian, it makes him poſſeſs his Soul, conquer the World, and have inward Satisfaction: With reſpect to God, it ſubjects the Soul to his Will; it waits upon God for ſtrength and a good Iſſue; it produces ſpiritual Joy and Praiſe.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe tenth Direction is this; if we would be in a fit poſture for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt labor after Patience under the will of God; this muſt be joyned to our Obedience, that we may be able to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60575:67"/>anſwer to all his will; As obedience reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects Gods commanding will, ſo Patience (which is alſo a duty) reſpects his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing one. <hi>Ye have need of patience, that after ye have done the will of God, ye might receive the promiſe, Saith</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.36. We are not only to do other Commands by Obedience, but, when Providence cals us to it, we are to do that of taking up the Croſs by Patience: Other Graces may help to bear the Croſs, but Patience takes it up upon its back: It is its proper peculiar office
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to make a man abide piouſly under the Croſs. This Grace may be conſidered two waies; either in that which it doth with reſpect to the Chriſtian in whom it is, or in that which it doth with reſpect to God; both ways it is of ſingular uſe in order to ſufferings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Patience may be conſidered in that which it doth with reſpect to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in whom it is; and thus three things may be noted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Patience makes a Chriſtian <hi>poſſeſs his ſoul, Luke</hi> 21.19. there is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the wordly mans patience &amp; the Chriſtians: The word by man endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours much that he may poſſeſs the things that are without him, but the Chriſtian bears that he may poſſeſs his own Soul. The Chriſtian, in a fit of Impatience, loſes
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60575:68"/>himſelf, and puts himſelf, as it were, out of poſſeſſion, not only of his Rational Faculties, but of his Graces too; at that time he acts not like a Man or a Chriſtian. When <hi>Jonah</hi> told God, that he <hi>did well to be angry unto death,</hi> Jon. 4.9. he was in his furious paſſion, more like a Beaſt than a Man or a Saint. <hi>If thou deal thus with me,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes to</hi> God) <hi>kill me out of hand, Numb.</hi> 11.15. The word <hi>(thou)</hi> here is of the Feminine Gender, <hi>At</hi> for <hi>Aita;</hi> the perturbation of Mind. made
<hi>Moſes, the meekest man on earth,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to fill up his words, or to ſpeak as he meant to do. It is by patience that the Chriſtian poſſeſſeth himſelf, and hath the free uſe of his Reaſon and holy Graces: While he is patiently bearing the Croſs, his Faith will roll out as Gold out of the Fire, his hope will fix itſelf in the unmovable Heavens, his love will burn within him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and his Glory. All the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Earth and Hell cannot put him out of the poſſeſſion of himſelf, or hinder his Graces from coming forth into act; he will be like himſelf in his ſuffering.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Patience makes a Chriſtian to be a Conqueror of the perſecuting World. The Overcomer, mentioned in the ſecond and third chapters of the <hi>Revelation of St. John,</hi> to whom ſo many pretious and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60575:68"/>promiſes are there made, is not one, that overcomes by Martial Fighting, but one that hath the Victory by Patient Suffering. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us</hi> (ſaith St.) <hi>Paul from the Love of Christ? Shall Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation or Diſtreſs, or Perſecution, or Famine, or Nakedneſs, or Peril, or Sword? In all theſe things
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, we are more than Conquerors through him that loved us,</hi> Rom. 8.35, 37. <hi>More than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors,</hi> becauſe they conquered by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; while their Bodies were ſlain their ſouls were triumphing over death itſelf. Thus St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 42.</note> that the Pagans were overcome, <hi>non a repugnantibus, ſed a morientibus Chriſtianis,</hi> not by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting, but by dying Chriſtians: Patience makes their Perſecutors ſecure them, and frame Crowns of Glory for them. This made the Martyr <hi>Vincentius</hi> tell his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor, <hi>Nunquam aliquis adeò bene ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivit mihi actu;</hi> no man ever ſerved me ſo much as thou haſt done. Patience doth ſo frame the heart to the will of God, that it makes a Chriſtian to be a King overhis Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, loſſes to him are gain, reproaches glory, confinement liberty, anddeath life: While he ſuffers in any thing, he is above it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Patience makesa Chriſtian to have inward content and ſatisfaction in ſuffering. It is the Apoſtles Exhortation, <hi>Let pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60575:69"/>have her perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing,</hi> Jam. 1.4. He that hath not Patience, is but a lame and imperfect Chriſtian; he may go a little way in Religion, as far as his Principles reach, but if he come to ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is beyond them, he will halt and turn aſide: But if a Chriſtian hath an effectual Patience, he is then perfect and entire, wanting nothing; he hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that may fill up his Chriſtianity or happineſs in this Life. The Croſs may come, but he hath Principles to bear it: Outward Bleſſings may be taken away, but he hath all in God. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> brings in patient <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Simb. ad Cateck.</note> ſtript of all, but only his God; ſpeaking thus, <hi>Quid mihi deerit, ſi Deum habuero? quid mihi alia proſunt, ſi Deum non habuero?</hi> What can I want, if I have God? What can other things profit, if I have him not? Patience gives the ſuffering Saint quiet and ſweet ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in God, and, not only ſo, but in the very ſuffering as it is a pious ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his will: There is a ſweetneſs and a ſecret reward in the doing of Gods will, much more in holy ſuffering for Him. The bleſſed Martyr <hi>Baynham</hi> at the Stake told the bloody Papiſts <hi>O ye Papiſts! ye talk of Miracles, behold here a true one, theſe Flames are to me a bed of Roſes.</hi> It's true,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60575:69"/>all holy Sufferers cannot ſay thus; but all of them find by experience, that there is a ſweet ſatisfaction in ſuffering for the good God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Patience may be conſidered in that which it doth with reſpect to God; and here are three things to be taken notice of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Patience ſubjects the ſoul to the will of God; when the Croſs comes the patient Chriſtians will with <hi>Aaron</hi> hold their peace; or if they ſpeak, they will do it in ſome ſuch language as that of
<hi>Eli, It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> Patience will inſtruct them to lye in the loweſt poſture of Humility, and to argue the matter with themſelves in this manner: Is God the Rector of the World, and ſhall we not ſubject to him? His Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is in all, his Power is over all, his Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs orders all; who can ſtay his hand, or ſay to him, what doſt thou, or call him to give account of any of his matters? To ſtrive with him is folly; to murmur at any piece of his Government is Rebellion; to think that things might have been better, is to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his wiſe and juſt Providence; And is he the Father of Spirits, and ſhall we not be under him? We give reverence to the Fathers of our fleſh, and how much
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60575:70"/>thers ſhould we be in ſubjection to the Father of Spirits and live? Our Saviour Chriſt, who ſuffered for us to ſweeten ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings to us, argued thus with himſelf, <hi>The Cup that my Father hath given me, ſhall I not drink it? John</hi> 18.11. After his pattern we ſhould ſubmit our ſelves to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, remembring that, though it come through bloody hands to us, yet it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the Father of Spirits; nay, and by the Father of Mercies too, who aſſures us, <hi>That all things,</hi> even Afflictions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, <hi>ſhall work together for good:</hi> In thoſe very ſufferings, in which man is cruel, God will be merciful: While the world hates and perſecutes us, God will embrace us in the Arms of his Love, and carrie us through the Croſs to the Crown of Glory: Upon ſuch accounts as theſe, Patience doth ſubject the Soul unto the Croſs. Our Saviour, the Mirror of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, being to drink up the cup of Wrath, expreſſes himſelf thus; <hi>not my will, but thine be done, Luke</hi>
22.42. His will was ſwallowed up in his Fathers, St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Commentary on thoſe words gives us this excellent note; <hi>Diſce Deo eſſe ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, ut non quod ipſe vis eligas, ſed quod Deo ſcias eſſe placiturum:</hi> Learn to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to God, that thou mayſt not chuſe, what thou wouldeſt, but what thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60575:70"/>to be pleaſing to God. Patience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es us to be pleaſed with Gods pleaſure, and to will every thing, not as it is in our own will, but as it is in Gods.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Patience waits upon God for ſtrength to bear the Croſs, and for a good iſſue out of it: We have both theſe promiſed in that of the Apoſtle, <hi>God will not ſuffer you to be tempted above that ye are able, but will with the temptation make a way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.13. In the firſt Clauſe we have a Promiſe of ſtrength proportionable to the Temptation; in the laſt, we have a Promiſe of a good iſſue out of it. Firſt, Patience waits upon God for ſtrength to bear the Croſs; this is the right Method of obtaining ſtrength: <hi>Wait on the Lord, and he ſhall strengthen thy heart, Pſalm.</hi> 27.14. Strength comes in a way of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks of a double patience;<note place="margin">De patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ. cap. 15.</note> there is <hi>patientia ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum;</hi> the patience of the proud; and <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia pauperum,</hi> the patience of the poor humble Soul: The one waits upon the will of man, the other upon the Grace of God: True Patience knows, that it is God only that can ſtrengthen the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner man by his Spirit, Eph.</hi>
3.16. No other but his <hi>glorious power</hi> can <hi>ſtrengthen with all might unto all patience,</hi> Col. 1.11.<note place="margin">De Martyr form.
5.</note> Notable is that of St. <hi>Auſtin, Haec eſt vox
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60575:71"/>Martyrum, omniatolerare, &amp; de ſe nihil praeſumere:</hi> This is the voice of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, to bear every thing, and to preſume of themſelves nothing. Thus the noble Martyr
<hi>Potamenia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spondan. Annal. An. 310.</note> being threatned to be caſt into a Veſſel of burning Pitch, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that ſhe might not be caſt in all at once, but piece-meal, that they might ſee, how much Patience the unknown Chriſt had given to her. True patience waits upon God for ſtrength; but this is not all, it alſo waits upon God for a good iſſue out of the ſuffering; <hi>Salvation</hi> belongs unto the Lord, and he gives many good iſſues to his ſuffering people: If they have an
<hi>encreaſe of Graces and Comforts,</hi> that's one good iſſue: If they
<hi>hold out and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere to the end,</hi> that's another good iſſue: If <hi>by death they paſs from the Croſs to the Crown, from a Temporal Life to an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal one,</hi> that's the beſt iſſue of all: For ſuch iſſues as theſe do patient Souls wait, till the Lord put an end to all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</p>
            <p n="3">3. Patience produces ſpiritual joy and praiſe: This is the difference between Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Patience and Chriſtian Patience; Philoſophical may bear adverſity, but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hath joy in the bearing of it. It was the ancient cuſtome of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to have often in their mouths,<note place="margin">Auſt. in P. l. 132.</note> 
               <hi>Deo
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60575:71"/>gratias,</hi> God be thanked for this mercy, and for that mercy: The patient Chriſtian, that looks upon the good iſſues of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may ſit down and ſing, <hi>Deo grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> not to Bleſſings only, but to Afflictions alſo. <hi>Job</hi> being ſtript of all, cried out, <hi>The Lord gave, the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord,</hi> Job. 1.21. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaking of Job, obſerves, That, when he had nothing of outward things, yet there were
<hi>Gemmae laudis Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſt. de Temp. Ser. 105.</note> the Jewels of the Praiſe of God found with him. Suffering Saints have ſo much of the Love of God ſhed abroad in their hearts, that they have
<hi>praemium ante praemium,</hi> a leſſer Heaven before a greater. St.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I ſuper abound,</hi> or
<hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow in joy in all our Tribulations,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.4. The gracious Preſence of God did not only cauſe joy, but the overflowing of it in his heart. St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith to the ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Chriſtians, <hi>Count it all joy, when ye fall into divers Temptations,</hi> Jam. 1, 2. That is when ye fall into Afflictions for the Goſpel: <hi>All joy,</hi> How can poor afflicted Souls reckon thus? In the Trial, their Graces appear in their pure beauty; Strength is made perfect in Weakneſs, Conſolations abound as much, nay, more than Afflictions; the beams of Divine Love irradiate the heart, and fill it with a ſweet
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:60575:72"/>ſerenity; Hope enters Heaven, and fixes upon the Crown of Life, and Heaven comes down in a Spirit of Glory upon the heart. Here is joy, all joy indeed; the total ſum of it in this life is made up in theſe things. It was the ſaying of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Mr. <hi>Philpot, That to dye for Chriſt is the greateſt Promotion, that God can bring any unto in this vale of miſery; yea, ſo great an honour as the greateſt Angel in Heaven is not permitted to have.</hi> It was the Prayer of Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi> the Martyr <hi>God forgive me my unthankfulneſs for this erceeding great mercy, that among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands, he chuſeth me to be one, in whom he will ſuffer.</hi> It was the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one of the Ancients, <hi>That it was peculiar to Chriſtians to give thanks in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity:</hi> Jews and Gentiles can praiſe God for benefits, but the patient Chriſtian can thank him for Afflictions: O let us labor after Patience, that we may not only ſuffer for Chriſt, but do it with joy: Thus our Saviour directs his perſecuted ones, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven, Mat.</hi> 5.12. Inward and outward Joys are very proper in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Saints, becauſe then they are arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the higheſt pitch of Chriſtianity, and ready to enter into the bleſſed Heaven, there to enjoy God for ever and ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:60575:72"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Some Inducements to ſuffer any thing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than part with the pure Religion. Pious ſufferers glorify God; they propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the Church; they give a token of Wrath to come upon Perſecutors; they are happy here and hereafter: Here in the proof of Sincerity, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God; hereafter in a freedom from all Evil, and a Communication of all Good.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>HAving laid down Directions in order to ſuffering, I will ſhut up all with a few Conſiderations, which may ſerve as Motives to induce us at Gods call to ſuffer any thing rather than part with the pure Religion, which is a Jewel incomparably more worth than all thoſe things, which we can loſe for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Pious Sufferers do glorify God in a very ſignal eminent manner: What is ſaid of St. <hi>Peter's</hi> death, <hi>That it was a glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, Joh.</hi> 21.19. The ſame may be ſaid of the death of all other Martyrs; we glorify God by offering Praiſe; much more by offering our lives for him: We glorify him by giving ſome of our Eſtates in Charity, much more by giving our blood
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60575:73"/>for his Name: We glorify, him, when we preſent our Bodies a <hi>living ſacrifice</hi> to him in Active Obedience, much more when we preſent them a dying one in Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive: Much of the glory of God breaks forth in his Suffering Saints; Free-grace ſhines out in the raiſing up Witneſſes to his Truth in a contradicting perſecuting World; Power admirably appears in bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them up with holy Joy and Pleaſure in the midſt of all the Torments, which men and Devils can invent againſt them. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent is that of the Apoſtle; <hi>Strengthned with all might, according to his glorious power, unto all patience and long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with joyfulneſs, Col.</hi> 1.11. Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is glorious in other things, but in his ſuffering Saints it lets out itſelf in a moſt illuſtrious manner: The Perſecutors have all Torments, all kinds of Death, but the Martyrs have all might, all patience, and long-ſuffering with joyfulneſs: As it was with Chriſt, his Power appeared in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, but above all, in that he trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed over Principalities and Powers upon the Croſs; ſo it is with Chriſtians, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power appears in other Graces, but above all in that patient ſuffering which overcomes the World: The Truth of God is in Martyrs practically proved to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding pretious. The Fathers, in the firſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60575:73"/>general Councils, were ſo earneſt for the Truth, that they would not exchange a letter or ſyllable of it. The
<hi>Arian</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> would not paſs inſtead of
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor the <hi>Neſtorian</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, applied to Chriſt as man, inſtead of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> applied to the bleſſed Virgin: All Believers ſeal up the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Truths by Faith, but the Martyrs ſeal them up by their blood alſo: Plainly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the leaſt jot or tittle of truth is more worth than life, and not to be ſold for a World. It was the pretiouſneſs of truth, that made
<hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſtand it out againſt an <hi>Arrian</hi> World, and
<hi>Luther</hi> ſtand it out againſt a Popiſh one. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Divine Worſhip is by Martyrs main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to be a Prerogative due to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. When all the World was given to Idolatry, the primitive Martyrs would die rather than rob God of his Honour: Their Sufferings told the World, that his Glory was not to be given to another, nor his praiſe to graven Images; no, not to ſave the lives of thoſe that were the only pure Worſhippers of him: Their lives could not be better ſpent than in ſuffering for his pure Worſhip; and after them, he would raiſe up others to Worſhip him. When the Emperor
<hi>Commodus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magd. Hiſt. Cent. 2. cap. 12.</note> asked the Senator <hi>Julius, Why he could not worſhip Jupiter and Hercules; Julius,</hi> ambitious of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60575:74"/>told the Emperor plainly, <hi>That</hi> Jupiter
<hi>and</hi> Hercules <hi>were no Gods, and that the worſhippers of Idols muh periſh in eternal Torments;</hi> and ſoon after he ſealed up his Profeſſion with his blood. <hi>Auxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> would rather ſuffer baniſhment, than ſet a branch of a Wine-tree at the feet of
<hi>Bacchus</hi> his Image, becauſe it had an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Idolatry. The ſuffering of the Saints for the pure Worſhip, proclaims it to all, that God hath a ſacred jealouſy over his Worſhip, and will no more part with it, than he will with his Crown. If we would indeed glorify God, here is the higheſt <hi>medium</hi> to do it; No Praiſes, no Alms, no Services, no Active Obedience do ſo lift up the Glory of God, as pious Suffering doth, in which we do practically, declare that we value him above all things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Pious Sufferers do propagate and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply the Church. When
<hi>Abel,</hi> the firſt Martyr was ſlain, there was a <hi>Seth</hi> raiſed up in his room. When righteous perſons are ſlain by Perſecutors, more of them ſpiring up in the Church. The more the Children of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> were afflicted in <hi>Egypt,</hi> the more they multiplied and grew, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.11. As the ground, that is moſt harrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is moſt fruitful; ſo God's People, the more they were ſtraitned under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of men, the more they were enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60575:74"/>by the bleſſing of God. The Roman Emperors did deſign utterly to extirpate Chriſtianity: <hi>Diocleſian</hi> (the greateſt Perſecutor of all, who filled the World with the blood of Martyrs) thought he had effected it; this Inſcription was upon his Coin. <hi>Nomine Chriſtianorum deleto, qui rem publicam everterunt:</hi> The name of Chriſtians, who overthrew the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, is extinct: But they were all in a miſtake; in the midſt of the Ten bloody Perſecutions, there was ſtill a new Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Chriſtians ſpringing up out of the blood of the Martyrs. <hi>Tertullian</hi> tels the vexing torturing Perſecutors,<note place="margin">Apol. cap. ult.</note> 
               <hi>Plures ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficimur, quoties metimur; ſemen eſt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis Chriſtianorum:</hi> The more we are mowed and cut down, the more we grow and multiply; the blood of Chriſtians is the Seed of the Church. St. <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith of the perſecuted Chriſtians,
<hi>Coedebantur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Civi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dei. Lib. 22. cap. 6.</note>
               <hi>torquebantur, urebantur, laniabantur, trucidabantur, &amp; multiplicabantur:</hi> They were beaten, tortured, burned, torn, killed, and yet they were multiplied. <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate learned this from perſecution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Diocletian,</hi> and upon that account he abſtained for a time from exerciſing Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and bloody Cruelties upon Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">Magd. cent. 4. cap. 3.</note> becauſe he ſaw that the Chriſtians by patient Suffering were multiplied and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60575:75"/>more glorious in the eyes of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Antichriſt hath ſhed a great deal of pretious blood, and the witneſſes of the pure Religion have been ſlain under him, yet hath the Evangelical Truth remained, and the Witneſſeſs, which were Slain, have from time to time revived and ſtood up in illuſtrious Succeſſors, who have held forth the ſame Truth, and ſpoke in the ſame Spirit and Power, as thoſe before them had done. When after the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacre there happened to be a great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity in Heaven,<note place="margin">Thuan Lib.
52.</note> and a Barbery-tree bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoming in a time unuſal, ſome Papiſts ſaid, That the thing was grateful to God, as if Heaven and Earth had rejoiced at it: But the Proteſtants took it as a ſign, that the Church ſhould revive and flouriſh again, like the buſh that burned, and was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. The true Church, which is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Chriſts blood, is not propagated or multiplied by Martial Arms, but by pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Sufferings: This is the true way to do good to the Church, and to continue the Goſpel among us; if we are indeed in a poſture for ſuffering, and ready to Seal up the Truth with our Blood, we may comfortly hope, that, whatever Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings come, the Goſpel and gratious Preſence of God ſhall not finally depart from our Nation.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:60575:75"/>
            <p n="3">3. Pious Sufferers do give an evident to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the Perſecutor, that the wrath of God will come upon him. When the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror
<hi>Commodus</hi> was worſhipping <hi>Jupiter, Vincentius, Euſebius, Peregrinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magd. hiſt. cent. 2. cap. 12.</note> and
<hi>Potentianus,</hi> went about and exhorted the People, to depart from the Worſhip of Devils, and honour the One only true God, leſt they periſhed with <hi>Commodus;</hi> and ſoon after they ſuffered Martyrdome for the ſame thing. Though all the Martyrs did not in words warn the Perſecutors, that the Wrath of God would come upon them, yet they all by their patient Suffering gave them an evident token of it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts the
<hi>Philippians</hi> to patient ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this account; <hi>Stand faſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in one Spirit, with one mind, ſtriving together for the Faith of the Goſpel, and in nothing terrified by your adverſaries, which is to them an evident token of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but to you of Salvation, and that of God, Phil.</hi> 1.27, 28. The Perſecutor comes with his Torments and Engines of Cruelty, to terrify the Martyr, but the Martyr by his Chriſtian Patience and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, gives the Perſecutor and evident to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that the wrath of God will come down upon him at laſt: If bloody Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who look upon the ſuffering Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, had but their Eyes open, they
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60575:76"/>would ſee cauſe enough to reflect upon themſelves, and ſay, <hi>Surely theſe men have a patience more than humane, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſuffer for God; and if ſo, we in perſecuting them, fight againſt him, &amp; may expect, that his wrath ſhould come down upon us, as it hath upon former Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Herod Agrippa</hi> was eaten up of Worms; <hi>Nero</hi> with a trembling hand, cut his own throat;
<hi>Trajan</hi> was thought to have poiſoned himſelf; upon the Perſecution in the time of <hi>Antoninus Verus,</hi> there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wars, Earthquakes, Inundations, Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, as ſo many Tokens of Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; <hi>Decius</hi> was ſlain, together with his Children;
<hi>Diocleſian</hi> died of fearful and miſerable Diſeaſes;
<hi>Julian</hi> in the <hi>Perſian</hi> war was mortally wounded by an Arrow from Heaven, and threw up his blood thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that horrible Blaſphemy,
<hi>Viciſti Galilaee; Valens</hi> in his war againſt the <hi>Gothes,</hi> was wounded, and, flying into a Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, was burnt with it by the Enemy. The temporal Judgments, that have befallen former Perſecutors, tell the after-ones what they may look for here in this World; or if they might eſcape here, eternal Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance will ſurely meet them hereafter. Our Saviour Chriſt will at the great day bid thoſe that did not feed, cloth, and Viſit him in his Members, <hi>depart into ever laſting fire,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60575:76"/>Matth.</hi> 25.41. much more will he ſay ſo to thoſe that Impriſon, torment, and kill him in his Members. When
<hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond of <hi>France,</hi> in his running a Tilt, received a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal wound in his Eye, he looked to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Thuan. L. 22.</note> where the poor Proteſtants were ſhut up as Captives for their Religion and often uttered theſe words, <hi>That he was afraid, that he had done the poor innocent men wrong:</hi> Conſcience then told him, what it was to perſecute. Oh! That ſuch things as theſe might ſtop Perſecutors in their bloody ways, as the Thunderbolt falling neer the Emperor
<hi>Anrelianus</hi> did him in his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Perſecution of the Chriſtians: The pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thoſe, that ſuffer under their cruel hands, tell them, that the wrath of God will fall upon them at Laſt. I conclude with that of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trianum.</note> 
               <hi>Quanto major perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, tanto gravior pro perſecutione vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta,</hi> The greater the Perſecution is, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier will be the Vengeance for it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Pious Sufferers are happy here and hereafter. They are happy here upon a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble account.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They give the higheſt proof of their Sincerity, that can be given: <hi>Abraham</hi> gave a great proof of his Sincerity in leaving his Countrey, and a greater in offering up his only Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> at Gods command; but I take it, the Martyr gives a higher proof of it
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60575:77"/>than is done in either of thoſe, it being more to part with all the World than to part with our Countrey, and to offer up our ſelves to God than to offer up a Son. The higheſt proof of Grace is in Suffering; That Faith muh be right that endures the fiery Furnace; that Love muſt be pure, that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically lifts up God above all other things; that Hope muſt be lively that lets go a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World for a future one; that Obedience muſt be glorious that continues unto the death. The Martyr hath a fair proſpect, with a comfortable ſight of his own up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, Conſcience gives an <hi>Euge</hi> to his Graces and Sufferings; nay, the holy Spirit is as a ſeal and earneſt of his Heavenly Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance; <hi>It bears witneſs with his Spirit, that he is a Son and Heir of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As they give the higheſt proof of their Sincerity, ſo they have the gracious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God in the moſt eminent way with them: All his glorious Attributes do, as it were, pitch their Tents round about them, and put forth their Virtues in a gracious manner for their good. His Power reſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to bear them up, how weak ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in the fiery Trial; his Wiſdom directs them how to carry the ſelves under the Croſs; his Mercy melts over them, while they are under mans Cruelty; his Love is ſhed abroad in their heart while they bear
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:60575:77"/>the World hatred: The Preſence of God will be to them in ſtead of, nay, infinitely more than all other Comforts: They may ſay, <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us? Rom.</hi> 8.31. Why? Devils can, wicked men can, but, <hi>Aquinas</hi> expounds the words, <hi>Quis contra nos laeſive &amp; prevalenter?</hi> Who can be againſt us to hurt us, and prevail over us? That which is of God, cannot be overthrown; they may break out with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in that gallant triumph, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor hight, nor depth, nor any other Creature ſhall be able to ſeparare us from the Love of God in Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. What St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith of the Church, is true of them a noble part of it;<note place="margin">In Cant. ſer. 79.</note> 
               <hi>Nec Verboſitate Philoſophorum, nec Cavillationibus Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum, nec Gladiis Perſecutorum potuit illa Separari à Charitate Dei, quae eſt in Chriſto:</hi> They cannot be ſeparated from the Love of God in Chriſt, neither by the words of Philoſophers, nor by the Cavils of Hereticks, nor yet by the Swords of Perſecutors: God is in the midſt of them, and they ſhall not be moved.</p>
            <p>Again, They are happy hereafter, &amp; this ſtands in two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are freed from all evils: In Heaven they ſhall have no Corruption within, nor Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion without; no Noiſe of Paſſion in the heart, nor rout of turbulent Perſecutors to diſquiet them; the will of the Fleſh ſhall have a total Circumciſion; the infirmities of the Body ſhall have a perfect cure; the Serpent cannot hiſs in Paradiſe; no temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations or miſeries can faſten on a Saint in Glory: There is Day without Night, Love without Fear, Joy without ſorrow, Life without Death, all Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:60575:78"/>without the leaſt mixture of Evil: There the bleſſed Martyrs ſhall be freed from all their troubles and miſeries.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are endowed with all good and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: The promiſes made to the Overcomer in the <hi>Revelation of St. John,</hi> ſhall be made good to them, they ſhall <hi>eat of the Tree of Life</hi> in a bleſſed immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; they ſhall have the <hi>white ſtone</hi> in a perfect abſolution; they ſhall be <hi>clothed in Robes of Glory;</hi> they ſhall be <hi>Pillars in the heavenly Temple,</hi> ſtanding there as ornaments in an immoveable Felicity; they ſhall <hi>ſit down with Chriſt in his throne, and judge their Enemies</hi> that condemned them; they ſhall
<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit all things;</hi> they that <hi>loſt all for God</hi> ſhall
<hi>enhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit all in him, who is goodneſs itſelf, and the fountain of it:</hi> They ſhall ſee him, who is the <hi>original and Chriſtal ocean of all truth;</hi> they ſhall enjoy him who is the <hi>ſupream good, and ſabbath of ſouls;</hi> they ſhall be <hi>ſwallowed up in the joy of infinite truth and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and their happineſs ſhall not be for a
<hi>time,</hi> but run parallel with <hi>eternity</hi> itſelf; they
<hi>ſhall be for ever in the Lord in the bleſſed Region:</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Civit. Dei. Lib. 22. cap. 30.</note> There, as St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> hath it, God who is all in all, <hi>Sine fine Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debitur, ſince faſtidio amabitur, ſine fatigatione lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabitur,</hi> ſhall be ſeen without end, loved without diſdain, and praiſed without wearineſs. In the next World there will be a vaſt difference between Perſecutors and Sufferers. The Pride and Cruelty of the one will be paid for in Torments and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Miſery in the Priſon of Hell, and the Patience and Suffering of the other will be returned in Joys and eternal Felicity in the bleſſed Heaven.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60575:78"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
